<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The watcher: or, The stone cut out of the mountains without hands, striking at the feet of the image, whose head is gold, and brest of silver, and thighs of brass, and legs of iron, and feet part iron and part clay, Dan. 2. 31, 32, 33, 34, 35. Or, A discovery of the ground and end of all forms, professions, sects and opinions, and also how they now are made as friends, and joyn hand in hand against the substance, the life and power of God, which is now made manifest in his sons and daughters (according to his promise) as hath been plainly manifest in several meetings betwixt the people called Quakers, and the people called Baptists, which is here describ'd. And also a description of the true Church, ...  / VVritten by a friend to all tender hearted ones, who hunger and thirst after God, who are hoping and seeking in forms for life, to the directing of their mindes, where and how to finde the true light which leads into the true life and power of Godliness, the end of all forms, where I rest with all who in spirit read me, who am known to them who are without, by the name, Iames Parnell.</title>
            <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E845_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R621</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872956</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872956</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168214</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 128:E845[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The watcher: or, The stone cut out of the mountains without hands, striking at the feet of the image, whose head is gold, and brest of silver, and thighs of brass, and legs of iron, and feet part iron and part clay, Dan. 2. 31, 32, 33, 34, 35. Or, A discovery of the ground and end of all forms, professions, sects and opinions, and also how they now are made as friends, and joyn hand in hand against the substance, the life and power of God, which is now made manifest in his sons and daughters (according to his promise) as hath been plainly manifest in several meetings betwixt the people called Quakers, and the people called Baptists, which is here describ'd. And also a description of the true Church, ...  / VVritten by a friend to all tender hearted ones, who hunger and thirst after God, who are hoping and seeking in forms for life, to the directing of their mindes, where and how to finde the true light which leads into the true life and power of Godliness, the end of all forms, where I rest with all who in spirit read me, who am known to them who are without, by the name, Iames Parnell.</title>
                  <author>Parnell, James, 1637?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Caluert, and are to be sold at his shop at the Black-spread-Eagle, neer the West-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Daniel II, 31-35 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian union --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168214:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE WATCHER:</hi> OR, <hi>The</hi> Stone <hi>cut out of the</hi> mountains <hi>without hands, ſtriking at the Feet of the</hi> JMAGE, <hi>Whoſe head is gold and breſt of ſilver, and thighs of braſs, and Legs of iron, and feet part iron and part clay,</hi> Dan. <hi>2.31, 32, 33, 34, 35.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, <hi>A Diſcovery of the ground and end of all Forms, Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Sects and opinions, and alſo how they now are made as friends, and joyn hand in hand againſt the ſubſtance, the Life and Power of God, which is now made manifeſt in his Sons and daughters (according to his promiſe) as hath been plainly manifeſt in ſeveral meetings betwixt the people called Quakers, and the people called Baptiſts, which is here deſcrib'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo a Deſcription of the true Church, and the gathering thereof by the Power and Spirit of our God, which is now made manefeſt in theſe later days, which ſo gloriouſly doth ſhine forth in the earth; ſo that all who have deſires to find the way of truth, need no longer walk in darkneſs, and ſeeking the living amongſt the dead where it is not to bee found; for now light is come into the world, and they that love and follow the light, ſhal not walk in darkneſs, bat ſhal have the light of Life; but ſuch as do evill hate the light, and will not come unto the light, that the light may reprove them, and this is the condemnation of the world, who love darkneſs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than light, becauſe their deeds are evil. <hi>Joh. 8.12. Joh 3.19.20,21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVritten by a friend to all tender hearted ones, who hunger and thirſt after God, who are groping and ſeeking in Forms for life, to the directing of their mindes, where and how to finde the true Light which leads into the true life and power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the end of all Forms, where I reſt with all who in Spirit read me, who am known to them who are without, by the name, <hi>IAMES PARNELL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON; Printed for</hi> Giles Caluert, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Black-ſpread-Eagle, neer the Weſt end of Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168214:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168214:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that happens to be the Reader of this Book, know this, that my mind and intent in the publiſhing thereof, was in relation to the ſimple hearted, who hunger and thirſt after Grace and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, to the directing and turning their mindes from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the true Light of the Lord Ieſus, which is not of the world but comprehends the world,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> and makes manfeſt the many wayes of the world, and the Snares, Bates, Traps and Nets that therein are laid, by him who is the God of the world, even the Prince of Darkneſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.</note> who rules in all the Children of diſobedience; now whatſoever makes manifeſt is Light, the which Light will diſcover unto them whoſe mindes are turned to it, the wiles and ſubtile ties of Satan, and ſo the ſimple wil come to learn wiſdome, and thereby be preſerved from the ſubtile devouring ſerpent, and therein the creature wil come to ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſiſts its ſafety and preſervation, and ſo <hi>Iſraels</hi> Tent comes to be found; for <hi>I</hi> in the Light ſtanding above the world, comprehending the many wayes that are in the world, and the deſtructions therein, with the many forms, judgements, and opinions, one claſhing againſt another, with their janglings and diſputes, with their earthly wiſdome, which is at enmity with God, and about thoſe things which they are ſtrangers to the life and power thereof, contending for that which fades and vaniſhes away, pulling down one judgment, and ſetting up another, pulling down one forme, and ſetting up another; and thus are building Babell,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſo are confounded with this confuſion by him who confounds the wiſdome of the wiſe, and brings to nought the counſell of the prudent, and ſo <hi>I</hi> ſeeing many poor creatures in this distraction, toſſed about with every wind of doctrine, and ſucking at the husk for life, and ſo gets into the comprehenſion, a deale of light ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry notionall knowledg, which is all but as chaffe, which the wind will ſcatter in the day of the Lord, &amp; ſo it will ſtand in no ſtead when the Lord comes to plead with all fleſh, for nothing will ſtand in the day of tryall, but what comes through death; thus <hi>I</hi> ſee many a poor creature loſt and toſſed in this wide wilderneſs, even this dark world, being carried captive by the prince of the Ayre, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true light to be its guide into the way of truth, which is the way of life and peace: now in the light which was before the world was, <hi>I</hi> do comprehend the
<pb facs="tcp:168214:3"/>
world, and the ground and end of all Forms, Sects, and Opinions, and ſo for ſome ſimple ones ſakes, and the tender hearted, have <hi>I</hi> here laid them open, and withall, directing the mind how and where to finde the true light by which theſe things are ſeen and read, and underſtood, and as it is loved and followed, the mind will be brought into the life and power, out of theſe fading empty ſhadows, unto the poſſeſſion of the ſubſtance, even the ſtone cut out of the mountain without hands,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 29.39.</note> the end of all forms, ſhadows and imaginations; and thus doth the ſtone which the builders rejected, become the head of the Corner, and thus the Creature is turned from the power of Satan unto God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168214:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> WATCHER ſtriking at the Feet of the <hi>Jmage. OR,</hi> A Diſcovery of the ground and end of FORMS, SECTS and OPINIONS:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the dayes of old, the Holy Men of God, (who was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the Spirit of God) did as they was acted and guided, moved and commanded by the Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God which dwelt in them, and here was their Rule: and alſo the Serpent as an Angell of Light, he acted and worked in his Inſtruments by the power of Darkneſs in oppoſition to the Spirit of God, the enmity being placed beiwixt the two ſeeds; and the more gloriouſly the true Light appeared in any age, Satan alſo reformed himſelf and appeared accordingly, in the ſhape, and form, and likeneſs thereof, as it is now to this day; but his was alwayes but the form and likeneſs of the thing but not the thing it ſelf, his is the falſe Light, the other the true Light, and ſo the true Light all along diſcovered him and made him manifeſt to thoſe in whom it ruled, but thus by his ſubtilty and deceit, he hath ever deceived the world and blinded the world, ſo that he might keep his kingdome who is the God of the world; as for example, <hi>Moſes</hi> a ſervant and meſſenger of the moſt high God, to whom God had revealed and made known himſelf, when he and <hi>Aaron</hi> was ſent unto <hi>Pharoah</hi> to require him to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go free, for a ſign unto him they caſt down their Rod, and it became a Serpent,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 10, 11, 12.</note> and the Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of Aegypt they was brought, and by their ſorceries and inchantments they caſt down their Rods, and they became Serpents, and thereby <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roahs</hi> heart was hardned, and thy would not obey nor believe, and thus the devill imitated and oppoſed the truth, but <hi>Aarons</hi> Rods ſwallowed up their Rods, ſo that it was manifeſt, that he that was with them was grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he that was in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:168214:4"/>And alſo when Iſrael had sinned againſt God, and done that which is evill in the ſight of God, the Lord God ſent forth his Prophets and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to declare the word of the Lord amongſt them, againſt ſin, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 20.9.</note> pride, deceit and oppreſſion, and all ungodlines, iniquities, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and rebellion, and they had Viſions and Revelations, and the word of God dwelt in them, by which they was led, guided, and acted; &amp; Satan he alſo wrought in his Inſtruments,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.</note> with a ſpirit of deluſion, and he ſent forth his Prophets with their viſions and lying divinations, and falſe dreams,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.30, 31.</note> and they cryed peace, where the true Prophets cryed wo; and the people hearkned unto them, and ſet them up, and the Prophets prohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied falſly, and the Prieſts bore rule by their means, and the people loved to have it ſo; but what wil ye do in the end thereof ſaith the Lord, by the mouth of his Prophet <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> who declared againſt it freely, and ſaid it was a horrible filthy thing, and he was perſecuted and the true Prophets who dwelt in the Light and in the power of God; they ſaw them to be ſuch as run,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.21, 22, 32. <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.</note> and the Lord never ſent them, and therefore they profited not the people at all, and they ſtole the word from the r neighbor, and they ſpoke a divination of their own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord, and ſay the Lord ſaid, when he never ſpoke to them; and they were light and vain, and daubed the people up with untempered morter, and ſewed pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows under their arm-holes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.18. <hi>Ier.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Ieremiah</hi> 23.</note> and healed the people ſlightly, crying peace, peace, where there was no peace, but they turned them not from their evil wayes, nor from their evil doings, and the Lord was againſt them, and the true Prophets of God (who dwelt in the Light) they ſaw them, and plainly and freely declared againſt them, then whether they would hear or forbear, and told them they built up <hi>Sion</hi> with blood, and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with iniquity, and the heads judged for rewards,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.</note> and the Prieſts preached for hire, and the Prophets divined for money, and yet ſaid the Prophet wil they leane upon the Lord, and ſay, is not the Lord amongſt us, as that none evill can come upon us? and they ſaw them to be ſuch as ſeeked for the fleeces, and regarded not the flock,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.</note> but fed with the fat, and cloathed with the wool, and made a prey upon the ſheep, but the Prophets of the Lord did not ſpare them, but freely and publikely declared againſt them, and they was perſecuted, and impriſoned, and deſtroyed, by thoſe who upheld and ſided with the falſe Prophets, Prieſts, hirelings, and deceivers, and they had then a way of worſhip unto God, with their new moons with their ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths, with their calling of Aſſemblies, and Prayers, and ſacrifices, and Burnt-offerings, which was once preſcribed by God unto Iſrael, but when their hearts was gone from him, ſo that they walked not uprightly before the Lord, then ſaid he, who hath required theſe things at your hands to tread my Courts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13.</note> bring no more vain oblations, incenſe is abomination unto me, the new-Moons and ſabboths, the calling of aſſemblies, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not away with, it is iniquity, even the ſolemn meetings, your new-moons, and your appointed Feaſts my ſoul hateth, and when you ſpread forth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168214:4"/>
your hands, I will hide mine eyes, when you make many Prayers, I will not hearken: your hands are full of blood, waſh you, make you clean, ceaſe to do evil, learn to do wel, ſeek judgment, relieve the oppreſſed, judg the fatherleſs, plead for the widdow, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. chap. and ſaith the Lord, is it ſuch a faſt that I have choſen, a day for a man to afflict his ſoul, to hang down the head like a bulruſh, and to ſpread ſackcloath and aſhes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him; wilt thou call this a faſt and an acceptable day to the Lord? is it not this the faſt which I have choſen to break the bands of wickedneſs, to undo the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed go free, and that you break every yoak? Is it not to deale thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are caſt out, to thy houſe, when thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thine own fleſh? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7. but this they did not do, therefore ſaid the Lord, theſe people draw near me with their mouths,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.26.</note> and honour me with their lips; but their hearts are far from me; and thus the Devill deceived them, and blinded their eyes in that age, with a profeſſion and form of worſhip, but their hearts he kept to himſelf; and this the Prophets ſaw in the light, and teſtified and declared againſt it, and left it behind them upon record, and when the time came that Chriſt was born, the Phariſes, and Scribes, and chiefe Prieſts had the Letter, the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and they could tel by them where Chriſt ſhould be born; and when <hi>Herod</hi> had aſſembled them together, he demanded of them where Chriſt ſhould be born, they ſaid in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.</note> for thus it is written by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo the Prieſts and Phariſes then was the keepers of the Letter, and they had the types, and the ſhadows, and figures of Chriſt the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and there they had a life, and thought in them to find eternal life, but would not come unto Chriſt that they might have life, but deſpiſed him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.19.40.</note> and would not believe on him becauſe he came not in the wiſdome nor in the pomp nor glory of the world but teſtified againſt it, and they was gotten up into <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire, but not into <hi>Moſes</hi> life, for they tythed <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Annis</hi> and <hi>Commin,</hi> but omitted the weightier things of the Law, Iudgment, Mercy, and faith, which they ought to have done, and not to have left the other undone, for that was a time when Tythes was due,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2. <hi>ver.</hi> 23.</note> for the <hi>Aaronicall</hi> and <hi>Leviticall</hi> Prieſthood, to which, Tythes did belong, was not yet changed until Chriſt was offered up, and they was faire ſayers, who ſaid and did not; and the hypocrites, who was hopt above the Light, and ſo was the blind leaders of the blind, with their faire ſayings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid Chriſt beware of the leaven of the Phariſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13.</note> and they turned peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the Light, and denyed the Light, and ſo ſhut up the Kingdome of Heaven againſt men, and would neither enter in themſelves, nor ſuffer others that would, but had gotten a wiſdome and righteouſneſs of their own, which blinded their eyes, and covered their ſins, ſo that they could not ſee their ſins, nor him that was the way, the truth, and the life, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did he pronounce ſo many woes againſt them, and called them whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168214:5"/>
Walls, and painted Sepulchers, who waſhed the outſide, but was the generation of vipers and ſerpents within: and thus Chriſt, who was the Light, ſearched them, and judged them who appeared faire on the outſide, but within full of uncleanneſs, but they could not hide themſelves from the Light, therefore they joyned againſt it, and the Saduces, and the Phariſes, and the chiefe Prieſts and Scribes, and the Herodians, and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> and the rude multitude, all joyned together againſt the life; and they conſulted againſt him, and took counſell againſt him, how they might deſtroy him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.1.</note> and the Phariſes came to tempt him, and inſnare him with queſtions; that they might get ſomewhat againſt him to bring him under their Law, but he fore-ſaw their deceitfull hearts, their plots, and confounded their intentions, and brought to nought their counſell; then they ſaid, if we let this man alone, all men will go after him, and ſo they ſought falſe witneſſes and took Counſel againſt him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.47.48 <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.59.</note> and Crucified him, and let <hi>Barrabus</hi> go free; and thus the devill blinded their eyes (in that age) with a ſtrickt profeſſion, and their own righteouſneſs and wiſdom, ſo that they could not ſee the Light and the Life, but perſecuted it, and ſeeked the living in the dead Letter, but if they had known him, they would not have Crucified the Lord of Glory, yet they was wiſe in their own eyes, and deſpiſed thoſe that followed him, and ſaid, none of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers believed on him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.48.49.</note> but an ignorant people that knew not the Law, that were accurſed becauſe they was the Publicans and ſinners, and they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves was the greateſt ſinners, but they healed themſelves up with their own wiſdome and righteouſneſs, and therefore ſaid Chriſt, they that are whole need no Phyſician, but they that are ſick; therefore he ſaid, publicans and harlots ſhould enter the kingdome before them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.11, 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.31. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.5.</note> but the blinde, the deafe, the lame, the dumb, and the Leopardies came unto him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on him, and were healed, and the poor received the Goſpel, but the Prieſts, and profeſſors, or the Phariſes, and Scribes, and Elders, and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, could not believe on him, that he was the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> but looked for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and theſe was the moſt zealous in their profeſſion, and builded the Tombs of the prophets, and garniſhed the Sepulchers of the righteous, and ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.29.30</note> if they had been in the day of their fathers, they would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the Prophets, and yet thoſe was the chiefe perſecutors of Chriſt, the ſubſtance of thoſe things which they upheld in the Law and the Prophets, therefore they was witneſſes againſt themſelves, and filled up the meaſure of their fathers wrath, and thoſe profeſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.39. <hi>Ver.</hi> 44. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.33. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.15.</note> and ſaid <hi>Abraham</hi> was their father, and yet denyed Chriſt, whom <hi>Abraham</hi> foretold of, but Chriſt told them they were of their father the Devil, and his works they did and would do, and thus he judged them for all their zeale and profeſſion, and ſaid, how could they eſcape the damnation of hell: Then after he was ſacrificed up, he appeared unto his Apoſtles, and ſent them to preach the Goſpell to every creature, and here they did not run becauſe the Prophets run, nor take up a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168214:5"/>
without them in the Prophets writings to do a thing, becauſe the Prophets was commanded to do it, but they was alſo acted and guided by the ſame ſpirit and word of truth which dwelt in them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.16, 17. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.7.8.</note> which Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was offered up, had promiſed, that he would ſend the comforter, even the Spirit of Truth, which the world could not receive, which ſhould lead them into all truth, and ſhould reprove the world of ſin, of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and of Iudgment, &amp; then after they had received the holy-ghoſt, they went abroad preaching Chriſt, and ſhewing thereby the fulfilling the Law and the Prophets, which figured forth and propheſied of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.</note> and this they declared in their Temples, and in their Synagogues, and they haled them out of the Temple, and out of their ſynagogues, and brought them before Governors, Rulers, and Magiſtrates, and the chiefe Prieſts, and their kinred, and the chiefeſt profeſſors (which was the Phariſees) was the head acters therein, but nevertheleſs they went on boldly, being filled with the power of the Holy-Ghoſt, without the fear of man, obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God rather than man, ſo they was not ſubject to the authority of man in that reſpect, but they was ſubject unto the Law of man ſo far as it was ſubject to the Law of God; and ſo they went on preaching <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſt,</hi> and many believed and were baptized, and received the Holy-Ghoſt and were converted, and it was ſo that the multitude that believed was of one heart, and one minde, and they was ſo far of one being exalted over another, or ſeeking themſelves, that not any of them ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.32.</note> that ought of the things which he poſſeſſed was his own, and the works of God went on in much power, the miniſters being acted and guided by the Holy Ghoſt. And alſo <hi>Stephen</hi> a man full of faith and the Holy-Ghoſt, he declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Temple, which God had once commanded to be built, and ſaid, <hi>Solomon</hi> built him an Houſe, yet nevertheleſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7.</note> God that made the world and all things, therein dwells, not in Temples made with hands, as faith the Prophet, Heaven is my Throne, and Earth is my Foot-ſtoole, and where is the Houſe that ye will build me? and where is the place of my reſt? hath not mine hand made all things? and he judged them and ſaid, ye ſtiff-necked and uncircumciſed in hearts and eares, ye do alwayes reſiſt the Holy-Ghoſt, as did your Fathers ſo do ye, and they gnaſhed upon him with their teeth, and fell upon him and ſtoned him, and when <hi>Saul</hi> was converted and became <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.17, 18.</note> his meſſage was for to turn peoples mindes from the Darkneſs to the Light, and then (ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi>) when it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in me that I might preach him amongſt the hearhen, imediately I conferred not with fleſh &amp; blood,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Acts.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22 &amp;c <hi>Acts.</hi> 17. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> &amp; here was <hi>Pauls</hi> call to the miniſtry, &amp; they was made manifeſt to every mans conſcience, &amp; was a ſweet ſavour unto God, both in them that believed, &amp; them that periſhed and <hi>Paul</hi> declared againſt the temple, and told them that worſhipped there they was too ſuperſtitious, &amp; he went into their ſynagogues on ſabboth days and reaſoned with them, &amp; they perſecuted him, and haled him before ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and there complained of him to be one that prophaned the temple, &amp;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168214:6"/>
a ring-leader of the <hi>ſect</hi> of the <hi>Nazareans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24. <hi>Acts</hi> 22.22. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8.</note> &amp; a peſtilent fellow &amp; a raiſer of <hi>ſedition,</hi> &amp; many cry'd out away with ſuch a <hi>fellovv,</hi> he's not worthy to live &amp; thus they ſuffer'd by the <hi>zealous profeſſors</hi> in thoſe <hi>daies,</hi> but they whoſe mindes was turned to the light, they was tranſlated out of darkneſs into the light,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 13 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11</note> and became the children of light, and was baptized by one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into one body, and had paſſed from death unto life, and had put off the old man, and put on the new, the old man being crucified with Chriſt, though ſome of them was drunkards, ſome ſwearers, ſome proud, ſome covetous, Idolaters, Adulterers, yet then they were cleanſed, and waſhed, and ſanctified, and juſtified, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God, and here was the Church which witneſſed the Spirituall Baptiſme, into the Spirituall Body, of which Chriſt is Head, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby ſet free from Sin, their Union and Communion was here, and the Bread which the Saints brake was the Communion of the Body of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.</note> and the Cup which they drank was the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt, and they was in Chriſt new Creatures, all members of one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and needed not that any man ſhould teach them, becauſe the anointing was in them, and to them the Croſs was the power of God unto ſalvation, though to the Greeks fooliſhneſs, and to the Jews a ſtumbling block; and in this Croſs Paul rejoyced,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</note> by which he was Crucified to the world and the world to him, and they was not conformed unto the world, but transformed by the renewing of their mindes, and had one Lord, one Faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.4, 5.6.</note> one Baptiſme, one way, one Teacher, one Life, and one She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheard, and one Prieſt over the houſhould of God, and one God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</note> being united by one Spirit into the bond of peace, and their converſation was in Heaven, and there was the Chriſtians, and though there was a time that when Chriſt was preached after the fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18.</note> ſome prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Chriſt through envy and ſtrife, and contention, to add affliction to <hi>Pauls</hi> bonds, yet in all this he rejoyced that the name of Chriſt was ſpread abroad, for there was many that believed not that that was the Chriſt that ſuffered at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and was crucified, as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf had not, and as there is many ſuch to this day, and ſo it rejoyced him that the name of Chriſt was ſpread abroad, but after his name was ſpread abroad, and many believed that that was the Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> then the Apoſtle declared againſt ſuch who had the form, but denyed the life and power, and ſaid, from ſuch turn away, for as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do they withſtand the truth, being men of corrupt mindes, and reprobates concerning the faith, and ſaid the Apoſtle, we preach Chriſt crucified unto the Jews a ſtumbling-block,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16.</note> and the Greeks fooliſhneſs, but unto them which are called both Jews and Greeks, Chriſt the power of God, and the wiſdome of God, and ſaid the Apoſtle, hence know we no man after the fleſh; and though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, hence know we him no more but he that is in Chriſt is a new creature, old things are paſſed away, and all things become new, and they that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168214:6"/>
with the affections and Luſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 26, 27. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.10. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5 25. 1 <hi>Iohn chap.</hi> 3.5. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.11 <hi>chap.</hi> 5.19.</note> and the Apoſtle preached <hi>Christ</hi> within the hope of glory, the Miniſtry which had been hid from ages and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and they that could not witneſs <hi>Chriſt</hi> in them, was reprobates, and here it was not ſufficient for them to ſay they believed Chriſt dyed for them, but he that believeth hath the witneſs within himſelf, and he that believeth is paſſed from death unto life, and he that believeth is born of God, and he that is born of God doth not commit ſin, and thoſe was they who was made partakers of Chriſts divine nature, therefore ſaith <hi>Iohn,</hi> as he is, ſo are we in this preſent world, and we are of God, and the whole world lyeth in wickedneſs, and they that are of God heareth us, and they that are not with us are againſt us; &amp; then the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> he ſpoke of falſe Apoſtles that was gotten transforming themſelvs as the Apoſtles of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 4.15.</note> &amp; no marvel ſaith he, for Satan himſelf is transformed as an Angel of light, therefore it is no great thing alſo if his Miniſters be transformed as the Miniſters of <hi>Christ,</hi> whoſe end ſhall be according to their works: and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> he fore-told of ſuch who through covetouſneſs with feigned words ſhould make merchandiſe of the people; and <hi>Iude</hi> he ſpoke of ſuch who go on in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 8. <hi>Iude</hi> 11. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.10, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for gifts and rewards, and ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi> it is the laſt time, and as ye have heard that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts whereby we know that it is the laſt time, they went from us, but they were not of us: Now the falſe Apoſtles was ſuch, as under a pretence or profeſſion of true Apoſtles deceived the ignorant, and brought in hereſies, and ſo Antichriſt is one (that under the profeſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) oppoſes Chriſt, and drawes from him in the life, though under a profeſſion of his name and of faith in him; and thus Antichriſt got up, even that man of ſin,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3, 4.</note> that is exalted in man above all that is called God, ſitting in the Temple of God as God, and ſaith he is God, and thus he decived them in that age as an Angel of Light in a form and likeneſs of Chriſt, but a falſe Chriſt, who bewitched them from the truth with a form and profeſſion; and thus Antichriſt hath raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the power of Darkneſs, ever ſince the Apoſtles dayes, over the world under a Goſpel profeſſion, yet I ſay not but that the Lord hath had a remnant in all ages to himſelf, who was zealous and faithfull in what they knew, but here hath been a long time of cruel darkneſs and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the Lord hath been a long time as a ſtranger in the earth, and they that were accounted to believe on God or Chriſt, looked at him as a God a far off in the heavens, without, far off, they know not where, yet they that ſaid they believed that that was the Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and that he dyed for their ſins and roſe again, and was ſitting at the right hand of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as that which they called their Creed, ſo then they was baptized with water and called Chriſtians, whenas before they were called Heathen, and did not believe that that was the Chriſt that ſuffered at <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> but now called Chriſtians and believers, though they were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing changed from the heatheniſh nature, and this was at the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in of the profeſſion of Chriſtian faith and Religion into England,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168214:7"/>
and thoſe had the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, which is called Scripture, and ſo was the keepers of the letters, and that they took to be their rule to walk by, as they do now, but knew not that which gave it forth, to lead them unto the life, but had the Letter and the form, but could not walk according to it, being led and guided by a contrary Principle, to that which gave it forth, ſo they gave their own meanings and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon it, ſo then all that were called Chriſts, were of the Chriſtian Church and faith, and ſo were counted believers; then they ſprinkled the children of thoſe believers, and by that were they entertained into their Church and faith, and thus came up Infants Baptiſme, for which there is no Scripture nor example, either from Chriſt or his Apoſtles, and yet they cal this an ordinance of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; thus they begin to ad their own traditions &amp; imaginations, &amp; all are by nature the children of wrath, and a littlewater on their faces doth not change them from that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 23.14.</note> but they grew up in al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of unrighteouſnes, as drunkenneſs, ſwearing, lying, covetouſneſs, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Idolatry, pride wantonneſs, envy murder, deceit, fraud, and maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the which was caſt out of the Apoſtles <hi>Church,</hi> and they was waſhed from ſuch things, and ſanctified and regenerate into the <hi>new-Covenant,</hi> &amp; reckoned ſuch to be without, as now <hi>Englands Church</hi> is upheld by: then they had their two Sacraments (as they call them) for which word they have no Scripture, and Infants baptiſme is one, and that which they call the Supper of the Lord, is another; and they had the carnall bread and wine, as the Prieſts and people hath now, and they give it to naturall carnall men and women, and the Apoſtle ſaith, he that eats and drinks this unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, eats and drinks his own damnation, not diſcerning the Lords body, <hi>And the naturall man receives not the things of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>and the bread which the Saints breaks is the Communion of the Body of Christ, and the cup which the Saints drinks, is the Communion of the Blood of Christ;</hi> and here is the <hi>Communion</hi> of the Saints, and the Supper of the Lord to which, he that hath not on a wedding Garment is not admitted; but Englands Prieſts knows not what a wedding garment is, and thus they planted their church in England, and other places, and then Biſhops was ſet up, and Archbiſhops; for which name there is no Scripture, and Deans and Prieſts, and Deacons, and Popes, and one ruled over another, and the Popes bore rule like Kings, but they found never a Pope in the Scripture, and the Biſhops they bore rule by their means, &amp; the Prieſts preached for hire, and the people loved to have it ſo, &amp; thus Antichriſt ſet up his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, under a profeſſion of the Goſpel, &amp; then tythes came up for to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Prieſts, contrary to any rule in the Goſpel, &amp; then Univerſities was ſet up, for to make miniſters or prieſts (as they call them) for the which they have no rule in the Scripture; &amp; thus they was ſet up by the wil and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man, as they are ſtil upheld, as the falſe Prophets alwaies was, &amp; then they had their long robes like the Phariſes, but not like the Apoſtles, for from them they have no ſuch example, then they ſet up theſe Idols Temples,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168214:7"/>
which the blind and ignorant now call Churches, or the houſes of God, for the which they have no example from the Goſpell miniſters, for God never commanded theſe to be built, and though <hi>Solomon</hi> built him one Temple, yet nevertheleſs when the ſubſtance came,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matthew</hi> 24.</note> he propheſied of its downfall and deſtruction; and <hi>Stephen</hi> witneſſed againſt it, &amp; was ſtoned to death by thoſe that upheld it; &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed againſt it, &amp; was perſecuted by thoſe that upheld it; as many of the ſervants &amp; meſſengers of God are now perſecuted in theſe Idols Temples, &amp; haled out and abuſed, &amp; ſtoned and impriſoned by thoſe that uphold them now, though theſe was never ordained by God, and then they got up into their Pulpets, the chiefeſt places in the Synagogues (as they are now) and called of men Maſter, and Doctor, and had the uppermoſt Rooms at feaſts, &amp; greetings in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets (as it is now,) and then they ſtole the Apoſtles words, as the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſtole the word from their neighbour, ſo did [and doth] thoſe; and put them into Chapter &amp; verſe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> took a verſe, and ſtudied from it a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination of their own brain, and added to it, but not from the mouth of the Lord, and ſo doth the Prieſts now; but they run like the falſe Prophets, &amp; the Lord never ſent them, therefore they profit not the people at all, and then with feigned or ſtudied words, through covetouſneſs they made mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of the people, as they do now, and ſo made a prey upon the ſheep as they do now, &amp; began to ſeek about for great livings, and fat benefices, and left a leſſer and ran to a bigger, ſo there was their beloved which they ſeeked for, as the falſe Prophets, which ſeeked for the fleece and regarded not the flock, but fed with the fat &amp; cloathed with the wool, and made a prey upon the ſheep (as they do now) and cryed peace to thoſe that put into their mouthes, and called them beloved brethren, and Chriſtians, but they that did not put into their mouthes, they prepared war againſt them, and brought a Law upon them, and haled them before Courts &amp; Benches, as they do now, &amp; thus they ſought for their gain from their quarter, and ruled them with rigour, ſo that until within theſe late years, the Prieſts raigned like Lords over the people, contrary to the practiſe of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, who made themſelves ſervants to all,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19.</note> and though they did ordain Biſhops, they did not ordain that they ſhould live of others Eſtates, or takes the Tenthes of the increaſe of others labours, and live like Lords over the people, but ſaid, a Biſhop muſt be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the Husband of one Wife, vigilent, ſober, and of good behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, given to hoſpitality, apt to Teach, not given to Wine, no ſtriker, not greedy of filthy Lucre, but patient, not a Brawler, not Covetous,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> one that ruleth well his owne Houſe, not a novis, leaſt being lifted up with pride, he fall into the Condemnation of the Divell: now try your Prieſts and Teachers by this rule, but they ſtood not to this who was ordained by the Pope, or by the wil of man, but was lifted up with pride and covetouſneſs, and greedy of filthy Lucre, as they are now, and ſo came into the condemnation of the Devil, as they do now, and thus your prieſts
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168214:8"/>
old father planted their Church and ſo ſet every thing in form and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to their own imaginations, and here is the ground and foundation of the faith and Church of England ſo called; and here is the old Fathers, and the old Authors that your Prieſts have ſo much talked of, and prated of their ancient Fathers, even the Popes and the Biſhops: and though now in words they deny the Pope, and the Papiſts, and the Biſhops and differ ſomething from the Pope in judgement, yet are in the ſame forms Cuſtomes, and Traditions, and are upheld by the ſame Laws as they was, when they was in the Popes and Biſhops Loynes, and thus Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt hath long deceived the Nations, and ruled by the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, under a notion or profeſſion of the Goſpell and faith of Chriſt, and one generation hath gone, and another come, and have not known the Lord that bought them, but by the hearing of the ear, and as thoſe that ſaw him knew him in whom he dwelt, bore teſtimony and declared of him, and thus the Prieſts could tell the people from the Records of the holy men of God, what God is, and what Chriſt is, and what faith is, and how Chriſt dyed for their ſins and roſe again, and that Chriſt is a Saviour and a Redeemer, and what the Apoſtles ſpoke and writ unto the Church free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they get and ſpeak unto the world for gaine and lucre, and ſo caſts the childrens bread unto dogs, and ſo ſeeds and puffs up the dark mindes of men with ayry knowledg, what they have gotten into their brains from other mens words, and their own imaginations, and ſo made and makes the people believe, that they are the means ordained by God; now many may ſee by this what lyars they are, and how they came up and was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and whoſe rule, practiſe, or example they follow in this they do, and they wil be found the Miniſters of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Look into their owne Records which they call the Book of Martyrs.</note> and ſuch as have long ſhut up, and do ſhut up the Kingdome of heaven againſt men, and would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enter in themſelves, nor ſuffer others that would, but ſo long as they had power would bind all unto themſelves, and thoſe that had any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Light, ſo that they came to ſee their deceit and ſeperate from them, they would ſcarce ſuffer them to live amongſt them, but praiſed be the Almighty who hath ſo weakned their hands and ſhattered their foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and cauſed his light ſo to ſhine out of Darkneſs, to cauſe them to be ſo manifeſt, ſo that all people who love Light better than Darkneſs, may now ſee how ignorantly &amp; blindly you have bin led, as ſtrangers from the father of light, after the vain traditions, cuſtomes, forms, ordinances, and imaginations of man, with a vain profeſſion and feigned faith, which you have gotten into the notion, but ſtil in you ſins and iniquities alive in the firſt nature, under deaths dominion, ſtill ſtrangers from the God of life, and from Chriſt the Saviour and Redeemer of his people from their ſins, and thus you lye under the power of Darkneſs and deluſion of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.10.</note> both Prieſt and people, for like people like Prieſt, and ſo ſaith the Prophet, and your Leaders cauſe you to erre by their lyes and by their lightneſs, and though you be full of teachers yet you are loſt for want of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168214:8"/>
true knowledge, and are ſtil led captive in your ſins and iniquities, after theſe who have gotten the form, but deny the life and power, ever lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and never comes to the knowledg of the truth in your ſelves, only differing from the heathen in name and profeſſion, judgment, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but ſtill alive in the ſame nature, in the fall under the Curſe, the children of diſobedience, in whom doth rule the Prince of Darkneſs, and you muſt have a Law without to keep you in awe and feare of the ſame, as they have whom you account heathen, but the Righteous needs no Law, for becauſe of tranſgreſſion the Law was added, and you are fighting killing, and devouring one another, as they do whom you account hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, &amp; you are Drunkards, &amp; Swearers, and Lyers, as they are, &amp; Scoffers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19.</note> &amp; ſcornrs and Revilers, and Back-biters, and Whoremongers, and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, and proud, and covetous Idolaters, and high minded oppreſſors, as they are, both Prieſt and people, and you are Idolaters, as they are, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and drinking, and riſing up to play, and you are envious, and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſuing, and rending, and tearing one another at the Law, both Prieſt and people, pulling down others to ſet up your ſelves, and you are diſſembling, &amp; cozening, &amp; cheating, &amp; defrauding one another of the earth, which is none of your own; &amp; you are perſecutots, &amp; ſtoners, &amp; ſtrikers of the innocent children, &amp; ſervants, &amp; meſſengers of God, and what ſin is there amongſt thoſe whom you account heathen, that is not amongſt you, &amp; doth abound, yea, thoſe whom you account heathen may condemn you inmuch of their practiſe; Oh! be aſhamed and bluſh you Prieſts and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of England, to ſee your Miniſtry and the fruits of your Miniſtry ſo laid open before you, and thus you are theſe who come neare the Lord with your lips and mouthes, but your hearts are far from him in the earth or elſe you would walk more uprightly;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 15.9.</note> but ſaith the Lord in vaine do you worſhip me, teaching (for Doctrine) the Commandments of men, but I know ſome Phariſees and Prieſts will be ready to ſay, we are no drunkards nor ſwearers nor ſuch like, but I ſay unto you, you are hypocrites, and your hearts are full of deceit, envy, wrath, and bitterneſs, covetouſneſs, pride, and earthly mindedneſs, and ſelfe love, and ſelfe-wiſdome, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and the greateſt oppreſſors of the truth, and Publicans, and Harlots ſhall enter the kingdome before you: Jeſus Chriſt the Light marked out your fore-fathers, and found them to be ſuch, though they was more ſtrickt and zealous than this generation: and by the ſame Light you are found in their ſteps, and thoſe things both Chriſt and his Apoſtles judged to be without, and condemned them out of the new Covenant, for there no unrighteous perſon can dwel, and there all wars are ended, and the ſwords beat into pruning hooks, and guns into plowſhares, and there is no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, nor ſelfe-exalting,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 20, 21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> but hee that would be the greateſt muſt be the leaſt, and in righteouſneſs are they eſtabliſhed, and they are far from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, and the Lord alone is their teacher, and there is no need of an outward Law, for to them there is no condemnation who walk not after the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168214:9"/>
fleſh but after the Spirit, and there is no reſpect of perſons, but all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one body, of which Chriſt is head, ſerving one another in love, and here is the new Covenant, and the Children of the new Covenant who are waſhed and made clean by the blood of the new Covenant, but you are Aliens and ſtrangers from this Covenant, who are in your notions and profeſſions; therefore all you ignorant people who are led by theſe deceitfull Prieſts and Phariſees, and diſdain to be wiſer than your fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, now ſee who is your fore-fathers, and the originall of your Prieſts, and who is your example, for you are out of the life and practiſe of the Apoſtles and the Children of Light, and by their life are judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, for they was mortified to that life which you live in; neither did the Miniſters of the Goſpell Baptiſe Infants with water; neither did they teach for hire, or ſtand up in the chiefeſt place in the Aſſembly; neither was they called of men Maſter; neither had they the long Gowns; neither did they reſpect any place more than another to teach or preach in, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept for conveniency;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.17.18 20.</note> for they teached in dwelling houſes, and by the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſides, or in any open place; neither did they give to the world <hi>Davids</hi> Conditions to be ſung in a Meeter; neither did they give to naturall men and women, bread and wine, which you call a <hi>SACRAMENT;</hi> neither did they uſe to Church women, as you call it, and take money for it; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did they take a Text of other mens words,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.21.</note> and ſpeak from it a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their own brain; neither did they ſtudy what or how to preach, but ſpoke as they was moved by the holy Ghoſt; neither did they teach people the Letter was the Word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.</note> or, that the Letter was the light, but they bore witneſs of God to be the Word, and Chriſt to be the light; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did they tearh people that they could never be free from ſin while they were upon the earth; but they preached Jeſus Chriſt the Lamb of God, who came to take away the ſinnes of the world, and to redeeme his people from their ſin, and to ſet them in the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, that he might redeeme unto himſelf a pure Church, not having ſpot or wrincle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26, 27.</note> or any ſuch thing, neither did they teach people that a houſe of lime and ſtone was the Church, or the houſe of God; neither was they ſet up or upheld by a Law of man, or came by the will of man, or ſtood in the will of man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note> but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, and from him they received their Meſſage and Command; neither was they brought up in humane learning, at an Univerſity (as it is called) to learn Arts and Sciences and take degrees, from Sir to Batcheller, and from Batcheller to Maſter of Arts, from Maſter to Batcheller of Divinity, from Batcheller of Divinity, to Doctor of Divinity, and had ſo many ſeverall Gowns, but the Phariſees loved theſe things, but the Miniſters of Chriſt was not ſuch, but moſt of them was ignorant, and unlearned in that wiſdome and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11.</note> but unto them it was given to know the myſteries of the Kingdome, but it was hid from the world, and the wiſe ones thereof; and now the wiſe ones of the world ſay, that is the meanes ordained of God, to come to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168214:9"/>
knowledge of the truth, and that is the originall, to wit, humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and deny all revelation or immediate inſpiration, and ſay it is cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for all which they have no Scripture proofe, for the Apoſtles never taught this Doctrine, nor preſcribed this way, therefore your teachers are ſuch as bring another Doctrine, and climbe up another way, who are not to be received but ſhut out for thieves, and robbers, who ſhut up the Kingdome of heaven againſt men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.1.</note> and wil neither enter in themſelves nor ſuffer others that would, and the Miniſters of the Goſpel never prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched up Hebrew and Greek to be the originall, but they preached the word to be the originall, neither took tythes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.</note> nor ever had a ſet mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or ſo much a year, namely, forty, fifty, or ſixty, or a hundred, or two hundred pounds a year, more or leſs, to abide in one place, neither ſued any at the Law for any ſuch thing, but all their care was to make the Goſpel free and without charge,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> neither did they take of thoſe that did not own them, as denyed them, but ſhaked off the duſt of their feet, and ſo left them, neither had they an hour-glaſs to limit themſelves by, or had a Clark to ſay Amen; but your Prieſts wil tel you now the Goſpell is publiſhed, and the Churches are gathered and planted: Oh! with ſhame might they ſpeak it, what Churches have they gathered, here I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore laid down their Church the ground thereof, the gathering thereof, and the planting thereof, and what they are, and alſo the gathering of the Apoſtles Church, and the planting thereof, ſo that here you may ſee the difference betwixt the one and the other, the one a form and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and profeſſion, the other the life, and power, and ſubſtance, and here alſo you may ſee what Englands Church, which Englands Prieſts have planted, now differs from the heathen, and now ſet Drunkards aſide, ſet ſwearers aſide, ſet lyars aſide, ſet proud ones aſide, ſet covetous ones aſide, ſet raylers aſide, ſet murderers aſide, and whoremongers aſide, ſet wild ones, prophane ones, and wanton ones aſide, ſet quarrellers, and fighters aſide, and hypocrites, diſſemblers, and perſecutors aſide, and back-biters, extortioners, and luſtfull ones, and ſuch like aſide, and then ſee where Englands Church is, which your Prieſts have made you believe they have planted, and let them eat no where but of their own vinyard, and it will make them go about to plant a better vineyard, or elſe to caſt off their long Gowns, and fall to dig with a ſpade, for ſome of them have ſometimes brought that place of Scripture to uphold their 40, or 50. or 100. or 200. l. by the year, where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>who planted a vinyard &amp; eateth not of the fruit thereof?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 19.7.</note> now according to this the vinyard muſt be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted firſt, before they can eat of the fruit thereof, and ſet thoſe aſide that I mentioned as aforeſaid, for the Apoſtles caſt out ſuchweeds and wild plants out of their vinyard, and then ſee where their vinyard is, which they have plaeted, &amp; let them only eat of the fruit thereof, and not rob others vinyards, and this is but equity according to Scriptures example, but they are ſuch greedy Doggs as the Prophet <hi>Iſajah</hi> declared<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:168214:10"/>
againſt in his time, and ſuch ravening wolves and foxes, as they live all upon the ſpoyle, and the fruits of others labours, and thoſe that hunts them out of their Vinyards, and Barns, and Flocks, and Heards; then they have a Law, even to devour them and their whole eſtates, and this is far from Goſpel Miniſters, nay, Jeſus Chriſt the Light ſaw their fore-fathers and marked them out to be the ravening wolves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15, 16.</note> in ſheeps cloathing, as theſe doth now appear to any, but thoſe that love to have it ſo, for ſo long as you put into their mouthes, they cry peace, peace, and ſpeak you fare, and calls you chriſtians and beloved; but put not into their mouthes, then they even prepare war, then they have a Law for you to take treble da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage from you,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3.</note> and ſo fulfils the Apoſtles words: Oh what a horrible fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thing is here committed in the land! are not they plaine ravening wolves, that would devour hoth body and ſoul? Now you people of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, conſider where you are, and whom you follow, and whither you are going, and ſee now who is your fore-fathers, and ſee now how you have walked by tradition and form, and have been blinded by a vain profeſſion and outſide-worſhip and ſo have taken Antichriſt for Chriſt, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Antichriſt for the Miniſters of Chriſt, and have put Darkneſs for Light, and Light for Darkneſs, and your fear towards God hath beene taught by the precepts of men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13.</note> and they have taught for Doctrine the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men, as I have before proved, how many things they have led you in by tradition, without any Scripture proofes, though to you they have been Oracles of God, but now they are ſearched, by the light, they are made manifeſt to be vaine heathenniſh traditions, and thus the blind have led the blind along, and many of them into the ditch; but yet I ſay not but the Lord hath had his people in all ages, thoſe who was zealous, and faithfull, and true in what they knew, but I know the Prieſts have been long utter enemies to God and his truth, and the tares have long covered the wheat, and in the time of ignorance God winked, but now the Light ſhines out of Darkneſs, and now is the ſeparation, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the ſheep from the goats, the wheat from the tares, and to convince the world of ſin, and of righteouſneſs, and of judgment, becauſe the Prince of the Ayre is judged, and now the Lord doth require all every whereto repent, and they that love the light will bring their deeds to the light, that the light may prove them whether they be wrought in God, and it is not to ſay you wil follow your forefathers, and go on the old way, for ſuch are they that hate the light and deſpiſe it, and love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deeds are evill, and ſo having drunk old wine doth not ſtraightway deſire new, for they ſay the old is better; and thoſe are they that cry up the old way, and cry away with new wayes and new Lights, and this is the condemnation of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19 20.</note> light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light becauſe their deeds are evil, Light is now to them who have alwayes been in darkneſs, and truth is new to them who have alwayes lived in deceit, but the light is the ſame, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168214:10"/>
ever it was, for it is unchangeable, and the truth is the ſame.</p>
            <p>So people take heed of obſtinancy and wilful blindneſs, and love not to be deceived, for now the light plainly and clearly ſhines, and here your old way is plainly laid open, what it is, and from whence it is, and alſo your Prieſts, and though they be more refined within this late years than they was before it is becauſe the Light is more broken forth within this late years, ſo that many is come to ſee their deceit, and declare againſt them, and now they are but the more ſubtiler and cloſer deceivers, Satan trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into anothe ſhape more like the light, but ſtill they have no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their great benefices, add Augmentations, or tythes, nor the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt place of the Aſſembly, nor their long gowns, though they are almoſt aſhamed of their colour, nor to be called of men Maſter, nor from ſeeking their gain from their quarter, nor from making a trade of other mens words, nor from their lying divinations, and ſaying the Lord ſaith, when he never ſpoke to them, nor from ſtealing the word into their mouth, and ſaying, heare the word of the Lord, when they never heard his voyce, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turns the wicked ones from their wickedneſs, nor the proud ones from their pride, nor the ungodly from their ungodlineſs, nor the prophane from their prophaneneſs, but are ſtil prophane themſelves, and ſtil proud and covetous, and ſtil ſhelter themſelves under the powers of the earth, as their fore-fathers the falſe Prophets alwayes did, and ſtil runs when the Lord never ſends them, but ordained and ſet up, and upheld by the wil of man, therefore they profit not the people at all, but only hath gotten a higher notion to feed the notioniſts withall, and ſo makes more Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hypocrites, and whited walls, and they are more whited over them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to deceive the world, but the pure light is ſo broken forth that they cannot hide themſelves, and many ſees the deceit of the Prieſts, and their folly is a manifeſting even to all, ſo that none need to be deceived by them but the wilful, obſtinate, and blind, who love to have it ſo, who love darkneſs rather than light, which is their condemnation, the light which reproves them for their evill deeds, and therefore they hate it, for every one that doth evil hates the light, and this is his condemnation, and no ignorance here is to be pleaded, and theſe are they that uphold the Prieſts and the Phariſes, but all who have deſires to ſee, may ſee; and now here is the Prieſts or the miniſters (ſo called) of England laid open, with the church of England, with their form, profeſſion, and outſide worſhip, with their ground, and originall, and ſandy foundation, and to be within, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the Heathen but in name, and form, and profeſſion, therefore down it muſt, though the powers of the earth hath long upheld them, more than any other ſect, ſo that they have continued ſo long, as they do not a little boaſt of, and thereby ſay they are of God, but let the Magiſtrate look to his office, and let the miniſter alone with his office, and then you ſhall ſee the profeſſed miniſters of England, to be the weakeſt of all ſects and forms, but Antichriſt hath had his limited time to raigne over the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168214:11"/>
earth, but now the King of righteouſneſs is riſen with a <hi>ſword</hi> in his hand, and by his mighty arm he wil <hi>overturn, overturn all until it come into his hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.8.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe own it is, and he wil bind the Kings in chains, and the Nobles in fetters of iron, and he wil brake the powers of the earth aſſunder, and all who oppoſe him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.</note> 
               <hi>and the Beaſt and falſe Prophet ſhall be taken, and all that receive his marke, and worſhip his image, into the Lake ſhal go ſmall and great, and there to lye forevermore;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 31.42.44</note> and this is the <hi>stone which the builders have reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which now is become the head of the corner,</hi> and <hi>whomſoever falls upon it ſhal be broken, but on whomſoever it falls, it wil grind them to powder,</hi> &amp; this is the <hi>Stone cut out of the mountain without hands, which ſtrikes at the feet of the Image,</hi> &amp; here is a blow to the foundation of the prieſts &amp; church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore now all people who are captivated under the Prieſts, turne your minds within to the <hi>Light</hi> of the Lord Jeſus, which reproves you in ſecret when you tel a lye, or uſe any deceit, which ſhewes you your evill deeds, and that your hearts are not right towards God for all your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſhorſhip and profeſsion, and that which cals for uprightneſs of heart and an holy life, and a change, and reformation, and a newneſs of life, hearken unto this, it is the free grace of God unto your ſouls, and teacheth freely, and by this you wil come to profit, for it teacheth godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and godlineſs is great gain, ſo that you will not need to ſpend your <hi>moneys for that which is not bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.1, 2.</note> nor your labor for that which profiteth not, nor to be led captive by your blind guides, ever learning, and never come to the <hi>knowledge of the truth,</hi> but ſtil in blindneſs and darkneſs, for <hi>you have a teacher within which is a more ſure word of propheſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note> to the which you do wel to take heed unto, as to a <hi>Light ſhining in a dark place, untill the day dawn, and the Day-Star ariſe in your hearts;</hi> this is the meaſure of the grace of God, even the free gift of God, which God hath given you to profit withal, which wil accuſe you or excuſe you before the throne of God, to which I now leave you, having diſcharged my conſcience concerning you, and ſo I proceed to the reſt of forms.</p>
            <p>Now within theſe late yeers the <hi>Light of Chriſt</hi> beginning to ſtir in peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts, ſo that many come to ſee themſelves in much darkneſs and ignorance of theſe things which they read of in the Scripture, and alſo the corruption of the Prieſts and Teachers, and what Reprobates they were concerning the faith, and that they profited not the people at all, but they had heard them ſo long, and ſtill blind and ignorant, ſo that many come to ſee their folly, yet their minds not being directed to the light, which ſhowed them this, and ſhould have led them out of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, upon which they ſhould have waited for direction to have found the way of truth, but they run without to the Letter in their own wils and wiſdome, and ſo would find out a way by their own wiſdome and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo went out to ſearch the Scripture, but with a wrong eye, giving their own meanings and interpretations upon the Scripture, and one cries this is my opinion, and another cries this is my opinion, and another cries this is my judgment, and thus they are confounded and divided into
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168214:11"/>
their ſeverall judgments and opinions, yet all ſtill in one life and one Nature, but onely confounded and divided in their judgments of what the Prophets meant, and Chriſt meant, and what the Apoſtles meant, but it is as a Book ſealed, both to the learned and unlearned, and none is found worthy but the Lamb to open the ſeals,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.11.</note> who is the light wherein lies the Miniſtry; ſo this is the cauſe why they whoſe mindes are from the light, are ſo divided and ſcattered in their judgments and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and one ſets up a form in his imagination, and another ſets up a Forme in his immagination, and one runs abroad into the world with his wiſdome, and he wil go preach up his form and judgment to be the truth, and another he wil cry down that form for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, anp preach up his form for a truth, and ſo many deceivers and falſe Spirits are entred into the world, and one cries, lo here is Chriſt if you can believe and be baptiſed you ſhall be ſaved; ſo they that can ſay that is the way, and that they believe Chriſt dyed for them, then they muſt be dipped in the water, and that they call baptiſing of them, and then they are of their Church, and then they call themſelves Saints, though they are ſtil in the old nature, and ſo in the fall, and in their ſins, and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and it is not the waſhing away the filth of the fleſh that doth change them; but becauſe they are come out from the Prieſts, and turnd into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judgment and profeſſion, they think themſelves Saints,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6.</note> and they read the Scripture of laying on the Apoſtles hands, and then the diſciples received the Holy Ghoſt; and ſo thoſe formaliſts and ſelfe-actors layes on their hands, but there wants the Holy Ghoſt, and thus they act, and form and imitate, and make the form or likeneſs of a Church; and they read of waſhing the feet in the figure, and ſo they dote upon the Letter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 13, 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> and waſh one anothers feet; and they read of delivering up to Satan, one for forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; for the deſtruction of the fleſh in the name and power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for in the ſpirit <hi>Paul</hi> diſcerned it, for ſaith he, though abſent in body, yet preſent in ſpirit, I have judged already as though I were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, concerning him that hath done this deed; and ſo thoſe formaliſts &amp; imitators, if any differ from them in judgment, they wil alſo deliver him up to Satan as they imagine, taking the Apoſtles words, though they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tax him for any thing; but his judgment differing from them, but they want the power; and here they are the Magicians, like <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres,</hi> oppoſing the truth, and thoſe are they that are called Baptiſts; and another form, they are more ſpirituall in their judgment, and they hold a ſpirituall baptiſme, and not a water baptiſme, and as many as hold with them, are of their Church and faith, and thus they are devided into ſeveral forms and Churches, and ſo have ſeveral names, and there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall judgments of one thing, under one name, and here is the confuſion of Babylon, with their ſeverall ſects, judgments, and opinions, and every one profeſſing the name of the Lord, and ſtealing the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and ſaying the Lord ſaith, when he never ſpoke to them, and here the difference from another, onely in profeſſion, judgment or opinion, but ſtil in Babylon, and Babylons faſhions, cuſtomes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168214:12"/>
and traditions, and fellowſhip, manners, and breeding, which is all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh, and at enmity with God, being in the fall, and thus they ſtand in the firſt nature, in pride, in covetouſneſs, anger, wrath, malice, fleſhli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and luſtfulneſs, and idle words, vain talking, fooliſh jeſting, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil communication; and to be ſhort, ſtil alive in the worlds nature, ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the holy God, and ſo under deaths dominion, and here I compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all forms, ſects, judgements, and opinions, by the light which ſlayes Death, and takes away its Dominion unto its ſelfe, to whom it belongs, and doth ſee them and judge them to be out of the light, in Darkneſs and ſo in confuſion, one claſhing againſt another, with their judgements and opinions, and here is the diſputes of this world, and the one cries, Lo, here is Chriſt in this form, and another cries, ſo here is Chriſt in this form, and none elſe, when as Chriſt is within his Saints, and theirs is a falſe Chriſt which they have ſet up in their imaginations, and here is the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and falſe Chriſts that are gone out into the world, who have decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved many,</p>
            <p>And hereis the ground of forms, a ſetting up a likeneſs of a thing, a figure or image of a thing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reve.</hi> 13.</note> but not the thing it ſelfe; and here is the beaſt and the image of the beaſt, which all the world worſhips, and wonders after; even <hi>Satan</hi> as an Angel of light, in his ſeveral ſhapes, forms, and likeneſſes to deceive the ſimple, and here is the form without the life and power, and here is the building upon a ſandy foundation, which all muſt come down,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 6.49. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.20.</note> who here the words, and talk of the words, and are ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the words; and hear is him that ſaith he hath kept the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Ordinances, and yet his heart from God after other lovers, who is ſearched and found out by Chriſt the Light, and here is the Spirituall Babel with its foundation, and Babels building, and Babels builders, and here is the Image whoſe head is gold, whoſe breaſt is ſilver and thighes of braſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.</note> and legs of iron, and feet part iron and part clay, but now is he come and made manifeſt, who ſtrikes at feet of Image, who is called the ſtone cut out of mountaine without hands, even Jeſus Chriſt the ſon of God; now after all this profeſſion of his name and of faith in him, but now he findes none in the earth who hath revealed himſelf in the poor deſpiſed ones of the world, and thoſe which have been counted the blind and ignorant, and as you have read the poor receive the Goſpel, the world was made by him, but the world knew him not, he came unto his own and his own received him not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> but as many as receives him, to them he gives power to become the Sons of God, to whom that promiſe is fulfilled which was promiſed in the dayes of old, by the father, that in the laſt dayes he would poure forth his Spirit upon all fleſh, and his ſons and daughters ſhould propheſie, and the young men ſee viſions, and if you wil receive it, this is the Elias which was for to come in the Spirit as he came in the fleſh, even the life and power of what hath been ſo long pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, which the Lord hath now manifeſted in his ſervants and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maidens,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168214:12"/>
whom he hath now ſent forth abroad,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.2, 3.</note> freely to call into the Supper of the Lord, even the marriage of the Lamb, and to preach his name no more after the fleſh but after the Spirit, and to preach him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the hope of glory, the Miniſtry which hath been hid from ages and generations, and they that will be his diſciples muſt deny themſelves and take up his Croſs and follow him, through evil report, and good report, through perſecution and through death, and who are faithful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til death muſt receive a Crown of life, and reigne with him for evermore in his Kingdome, of which there is no end neither beginning, over which he is made heire and King, bleſſed be Jehovah, ſing <hi>Haelalujah</hi> to his name all ye that know him.</p>
            <p>And now that his name is ſpreading abroad, and his meſſage declaring by the mouth of his faithful meſſengers; thoſe who have long talked of his name, and ſo long profeſſed his name knows him not, neither believes on him, but are found hypocrites, and diſſemblers, and blind leaders of the blind; whited walls, and painted Sepulchers, but within full of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, hypocriſie, and deceit, even the generation of vipers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and thoſe will not receive the meſſage, but makes light of it, and ſaith, they believe on a Chriſt at Jeruſalem, and now in the heavens far off they know not where, and they cry, he hath done all for us, and hath ſatisfied for our ſins, and they ſhal not be imputed to us ſay they; and they cry out this is a new Light, and a ſtrange Light, and we know not whence it is, but they ſay they wil keep to the old Rule, the Scriptures (which they call the word of God, and the old way) though they be meer ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the life of the Scriptures; but it is that the Scripture might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled upon them, as Chriſt ſaith, for judgemet am I come into the world that they which ſee not might ſee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.39.</note> and that they which ſee might be made blind, as their forefathers profeſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſaid, we know that God ſpake unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> but as for this fellow, we know not whence he is, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.29. and they ſaid, God was their Father, but Jeſus Chriſt anſwered them and ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>If ye were Abrahams children ye would do the works of Abraham,</hi> and he alſo ſaid, <hi>If God were your Father then would you love me, for I proceeded forth and came from him, but ſaith he, ye are of your Father the Devill, and his works you do and will do;</hi> and thus are the Phariſaicall profeſſors of theſe times, marked out to be in the ſteps of their fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for this is the ſame Chriſt that ſuffered at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but they are blind and cannot ſee, neither (indeed) do believe the Scripture, nor walk according to it, but are in the old and broad way of the world, wherein their fore-fathers walked, and led many to deſtruction, but if theſe did believe the Scripture, they would believe on this light which is come into the world, which the Scripture bares teſtimony of, even the Spirit of truth which the world cannot receive, and ſome of them ſcoff and ſcorn, and revile, reproach and ſlander, and rayle at the meſſengers of Truth, and ſome ſtrike them, and ſtone them, and buffer them, and ſtock
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168214:13"/>
them, and whip them, and impriſon them, and deſpitefully uſe them, yet they are made able through the power of him that hath ſent them, for to go on in boldneſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.4, 5, 6.</note> but thoſe perſecutors are not found worthy, <hi>Therefore the Lord wil ſend forth his Armies and deſtroy theſe murderers and burn up their City:</hi> and theſe are they that have profeſſed to be his near kindred, friends, and acquaintance, but now are found ſtrangers who propheſied in his name, and in his name done many wondrous works, and yet they muſt depart for works of iniquity, he knows them not; now read your ſelves you wicked ones, you murderers, you rude multitude, you Prieſts, you Phariſes and profeſſors, you formaliſts, ſelfe-actors, and im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tators, for now all joyne hand in hand, and <hi>Gog, and Magog</hi> joyns in Battel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lamb, and <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> is made friends, and you chiefe Prieſts and Phariſes who are the profeſſors of theſe times, and you Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and you rude and bruitiſh ones, and you formaliſts and ſectaries now at the comming of Chriſt in the Spirit, even the ſubſtance of what you have long talked of, all joyned together in one, who formerly have been at great diviſion and wars among your ſelves, but now you are made friends, and muſter up all your ſtrength againſt the ſubſtance, even Jeſus Chriſt, whom you (as your fore-fathers did) call a blaſphemer, a ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, a deceiver, and a devil; and now the rude multitude they ſtand up for their Prieſts, and they fall upon the meſſengers of Chriſt when they come into their Synagogues, and they hale them out of their Synagogues, and ſtrike them, and buffet them, and deſpitefully uſe them, and ſtone them, as their fore-father ever did, and the Prieſts they ſeek to Rulers &amp; Magiſtrates, and hales them before them, and they perſecute them and impriſon them, as their fore-fathers ever did, and the phariſes and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent hypocriticall rotten profeſſors, they ſide with the Prieſts, and goes about railing, and evill ſpeaking of the truth, learning and inſenſing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples mindes againſt it, with their lyes and ſlanders and reproaches to preſent it odious to all people, and alſo fauning, and crouching, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to Magiſtrates, to act in their wills and perſecute, as their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alwayes did againſt the ſame ſeed, and likewiſe the formaliſts and ſectaries do the ſame, and thus they that were after the fleſh alwayes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted them that were after the ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29.</note> and yet theſe are ready to cry out what hard hearted Jews was thoſe that crucified Chriſt, and perſecuted his Apoſtles, and if they had been in thoſe dayes they would not have been partakers with them in the blood of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they are now found the ſame generation of perſecutors, perſecuting the righteous ſeed, and ſo they fil up the meaſure of their fathers wrath, that upon them might come all the righteous blood-ſhed from righteous <hi>Abel</hi> until now.</p>
            <p>And now the Prieſts and the Baptiſts can agree, and they joyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Prieſts calls them honeſt men, and the Baptiſts calls them Gentlemen of Divinity, and the Baptiſts and Independents, they joyne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168214:13"/>
together, and the Independants, and the Presbiterians, they joyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all againſt the life and power, which the Lord hath now manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Sons and Daughters, and hath ſent them to declare and lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their hypocriſie and deceit, which they have long covered with a Goſpell-like profeſſion, but now all their coverings are found too narrow before the Light which is come now into the world, to convince and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them of their ſin, of their righteouſneſs, and of their judgment; and therefore now they have enough to do to joyne together with all their ſtrength and wiſdome, to put out this light, and ſo they endeavour to ſew their tares in peoples hearts, and all the wayes they can invent to deſtroy the work which now is begun, and as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do they withſtand the truth, according to the propheſie of the Apoſtle, <hi>being men of corrupt mindes, and reprobates concerning the ſaith,</hi> which I have much experience in ſeverall meetings which I have had with the teachers of the baptized people, which ſhall follow in order after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>But the more they ſtrive in their wills and wiſdomes, the more doth the work of the Lord proſper and go on, and flouriſh by his mighty power, and outſtretched arm, and their ſhame, and folly, and down-fall the more appear, and when they have done all they can, they ſhall be glad to lay down their grounds, and bow unto this truth which they now ſo oppoſe, and every tongue ſhall confeſs it though to their condemnation, who do now oppoſe and gain-ſay it, wo unto ſuch, they ſhall periſh in the gain-ſaying of Core, <hi>And the time ſhal come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.25.</note> 
               <hi>that when the maſter of the houſe ſhall have ſhut the dore, they ſhall knock and ſhall ſtrive to enter and ſhall not be able,</hi> all who now oppoſe and reject the Counſell of the Lord and will not hearken now they are called.</p>
            <p>And thus the LORD will exhalt his SONNE in his SAINTS, when his ENEMIES ſhall bee his Foot ſtole, and be made to bow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
            <p>And thus doth all Sects, Judgements, and Opinions, joyne in one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Life and Subſtance, they being all ſprung from one Root, ſo make up all one Image, whoſe head is Gold, Breaſt of ſilver, whoſe Thighes is Braſs, and Legs of Iron, and feet part of Iron and part of Clay; and the Stone cut out of the Mountain without hands, which ſtrikes at the feet of the Image.</p>
            <p>Now the head of the Image which is of gold, &amp; thoſe that have had a light ſhining into them, and have had a ſight of many things, &amp; have ſeen the emptineſs of many forms, and have gotten the thing in their compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, &amp; have a notion above others, of much of that which is now wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed &amp; poſſeſt in life by the faithful, &amp; there have been exalted &amp; got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten up a life therein, and a falſe reſt, but have loſt the light which once ſhined into them, by catching the thing in their Comprehenſion, and ſo got it in the notion, but did not obey nor ſuffer the death of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168214:14"/>
the Croſs, and the breaſt of the Image which is of Silver, and the thighes of braſs, are the reſt of the ſects, and opinions, and forms, and likeneſſes; which are more glorious one than another, for as I ſaid before; Satan can imitate every appearance of the true Light, in his forms, ſhapes, and likeneſſes, and the more glorious the light appears in any creature, ſo doth he refine himſelf, and appear more glorious to deceive the ſimple; ſo that many (by the light of God ſtirring in them) have come to ſee the deceit and emptineſs in one form, and how they have been deceived there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then preſently the deceit appears in another more glorious ſhape or form, and calls that the truth, and the creature ſtil looking without from the Light, within it is inſnared there, again ſtil painted with the Scripture words, and then the creature thinks its a Saint in that form, whenas its but a painted Sepulcher, ſtil in the old nature; and under the power of the ſame deceit, but the Croſs tryes all, for there all forms and profeſſions miſſes and comes ſhort, ſo that many a creature hath paſſed through many forms, and hath thought it ſelf a Saint in every form, but coming, yea, but to ſee the Croſs which they are to take up before they can be the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt, and there have ſtumbled and cryed out, it is hard and ſtraight, and goes away ſorrowfull, I know this is witneſſed and anſwered in many conſciences, for here every mans faith and works comes to the tryall, and ſo to ſome the preaching of the <hi>Croſs</hi> is fooliſhneſs, and to ſome a ſtumbling-block, but unto them that believe and take it up, it is witneſſed the power of God unto ſalvation, and ſuch rejoyces in it with <hi>Paul,</hi> who are crucified to the world and the world to them, upon whom the ends of the world are come, but it would be an eaſie thing to the fleſh if that was all,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.</note> to turn out of one profeſſion into another, and out of one form and judgement into another, but the way to life is through death.</p>
            <p>And the Legs of the Image, which is of Iron, is the Beaſt, or the power of the Beaſt, upon which theſe ſtand, where lies their ſtrength; and the feet of the Image, which is part of Iron and part of Clay, are the Prieſts and Phariſes, joyned to the powers of the earth, which upholds them, for but for that, as I ſaid before, they are the weakeſt of all forms, and ſo they are the part of clay, and the power that upholds them, is that part of Iron which is the ſtrongeſt of the mettalls; and the watcher, or the ſtone cut out of the mountain without hands, which ſtrikes at the feet of the Image, is the King of righteouſneſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 17.12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>even he that rides upon the white horſe, out of whoſe mouth goes a ſharp ſword, whoſe name is called the word of God, who comes to ſtrike at the powers of the earth, even the Kings of the earth, who have given their power unto the Beaſt, and joyne in war againſt the Lamb, but the Lamb ſhall overcome, and he will overturn all untill it come into his hand whoſe own it is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1.</note> 
               <hi>and the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet that hath thus deceived the nations, and all that receive the mark of the Beaſt, and worſhip his Image, ſhall be taken and caſt into the lake that burneth for ever,</hi> which was of old prepared for them, <hi>and he wil create new heavens and new earth, wherein dwelleth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168214:14"/>
where there ſhal not be war any more, but he ſhall reigne in peace with his Saints for evermore.</hi> Oh bleſſed are all they that fight in this Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and here lay down their lives, they ſhall take them up again with an everlaſting Crown, and reigne for evermore, ſinging Halelujah to their king, to whom be all praiſe, honour, power, dominion, and thanks for evermore, Amen: And thus ſhall this great Image be broken to pieces, by the Stone cut out of the mountain without hands, which wil become a heavy mountain, even a burdenſome ſtone to all nations, but upon this Mountain ſhall the true Church ſtand, as a City ſet on a Hill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.14.</note> that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hid: and thus I have laid down the ground and end of all ſects, forms and profeſſions, with a blow to this great Image, with a weapon which is not carnall but ſpirituall, he that can receive it let him.</p>
            <p>And now concerning the CHURCH which is now gathering and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, not by the wil of man, nor by the wiſdome of many, but by the wil and power, and ſpirit of God, which according unto his promiſe he hath poured down upon his Sons and Daughters now in theſe latter dayes, by which we are carried abroad in the power of the Almighty, now to declare abroad his powerfull Truth, which the Lord hath decreed ſhall prevail upon the hearts of the people, which is glad tydings of great joy, unto them that receive it, but unto the ſtubborn and ſtiff-necked and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, tydings of wo and miſery, and though the meſſengers of the Goſpell are by ſome rejected, reviled, reproached, ſcoffed, and ſcorned, ſtocked, ſtoned, and impriſoned, and deſpitefully uſed, ſlandered, and abuſed, yet nevertheleſs, bleſſed be the name of the Lord, there are ſome found worthy and do receive with much joy the meſſengers of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.</note> ſo that they know how beautifull are the feet of thoſe that bring glad tydings, to the reviving the juſt witneſs for God, and raiſing up to life the dead, and ſo the living comes to know and praiſe the Lord, and ſo the juſt comes to reign, and the wicked comes to be judged, and the minde comes to be turned from the darkneſs to the light, to which we do preach in every creature, and to the ſame are made manifeſt, and known to them who do like to retain it in their mindes, and from whence we come, and the teſtimony which we do declare; but they that do not receive it, to them we are not known, and therefore are by them eſteemed as deceivers, and deluders, vagabonds, and wanderers, and the like; yet at all this we do not wonder, for we read the ſervant is not greater than his lord, for if they have called the Maſter of the Houſe <hi>Belzebub,</hi> how much more thoſe of his houſhould, and if they had known him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.24, 25</note> they would not have cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Lord of glory, yet nevertheleſs we have a witneſs in every Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, both in them that believe, and in them that periſh, unto which we do clear our conſciences, and leave all without excuſe by the ſame, which wil anſwer for us in the mighty day, though to the condemnation of thoſe that hate it, wherein we have our great joy above all our ſufferings, but as many as receives this, to them he gives Power
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168214:15"/>
to bccome the Sons of God, and thoſe are they who are led and guided by the one ſpirit of Truth, which the world cannot receive, even <hi>the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of whom you have heard ſhould come,</hi> by which they are ſeperated out of the world, &amp; redeemed out of the rudiments &amp; polutions therof, their faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their cuſtomes, their words, their ways, their manners, their breeding, their fellowip, love and friendſhip, their honor and glory, and their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſo are become ſtrangers to the world, and ſo are hated of the world, becauſe they are not of the world, and the enmity ſtands betwixt the two ſeeds; but while they was of the world the world loved them, but now they are gathered out of the world, and ſeperated from the world, and teſtifies againſt the world both in words and actions, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the enmity is raiſed in the world againſt the <hi>righteous ſeed,</hi> and thoſe are they upon whom the ends of the world are come, to <hi>whom it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdome,</hi> though to the world in Parables; and thoſe are they that are come with a mighty arm and power, to turn the world upſide down, whom the Lord hath gathered, and is a gathering out of the world by his owne Spirit of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> to walk in the way of <hi>Truth,</hi> even the way of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> where the Ranſomed of the Lord doe walk, and ſerve and worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth, and ſuch is the Father ſeeking to worſhip him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.23, 24</note> in whom he is, in doing his own ork, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to deſtroy the old Creation, and create <hi>new Heavens and new Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs,</hi> and thoſe are they that are the new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in whom this new work is witneſſed, in whom the Father hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his Son, that in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh he might condemn ſin in the fleſh, and to bind the ſtrong man, and caſt him out of his houſe, and ſpoyl his goods, and ſo to deſtroy the works of the Devil, and to cut down the Man of Sin, even that ſon of perdition who is exalted above all that is called GOD, ſitting in the Temple of God as God, and ſaith he is God; this is he by whom the world is deceived, who is the God of the world, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Prince of Darkneſs, who rules in all the Children of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> in the light, <hi>the whole world lies in wickedneſs,</hi> and unto this doth Chriſt come with a ſword for to make war with him, and to take and bind him, and caſt him into utter darkneſs, and ſo to take his Kingdom from him, and to rule himſelf in righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And this is the King of the SAINTS, who is now come to redeem unto himſelf a pure people, and to waſh them and clenſe them from their ſinnes by his BLOOD, and ſo to waſh away all filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, and this is the Baptiſm by which they are received into his Church and Faith, and here is the effect of his BLOOD wrought in MAN; and thus he doth and will manifeſt his mighty power, to purifie, and clenſe, and make Man a fit Temple for himſelf to dwell in, and thus is GOD with us, manifeſted in Fleſh, and thus are the Saints Bodies made the TEMPLES of the HOLY GHOST, and thus is the word
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168214:15"/>
of Life and Reconciliation witneſſed, to the raiſing up the Soul to Life, and reconciling the Soul to GOD, and thoſe are they that are begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and born again of the Immortal Word which dwelleth and abideth for ever, and here is the Houſhold of God, the Houſhold of Faith, and the Houſhold of Love,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1.</note> who ſpeak the things which they have heard and ſeen, and taſted of the good Word of Life, which was in the beginning, and thoſe are the children of Light who are gathered out of the darke Forms, Judgments, and Opinions, into the life and power of godlineſs, to walk in the Light of Life, wherein they are gathered and united by the one Spirit of Love and Life, into one body, of which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is head: and here is the true <hi>Church</hi> which the Lord is a gathering, and waſhing, and cleanſing, and purifying by his Spirit, that he may redeem unto himſelf a pure <hi>Church, not having ſpot or wrinckle,</hi> or any ſuch thing, whoſe inſides are waſhed and made clean through the Word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.</note> by which they are reconciled into the love and union which ſprings from the Life of God, and here is the Vine and the Branches, and here is the communion of the <hi>Church,</hi> all feeding upon one Bread, all drinking upon one cup, this is Chriſt the Life of the Saints, and as many as are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into this Church, partake of this communion, and thoſe are they which have denied themſelves, and have borne the Croſs of Chriſt, by which they are crucified to the world, and the world to them, who are gathered into one Covenant of Life, where all are Fellow-Servants, under one MASTER, who ſerve one another in love and meekneſſe: and here is the true Humility in the HEART wrought, and here is the true waſhing of feet without Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which ſome are imitating without for LIFE, but falls ſhort, for the heart the Lord requires.</p>
            <p>And thus is the Church of Chriſt gathered by one ſpirit, and by the ſame circumciſed and baptiſed into one Light, and Life, and Power, where all dwell as MEMBERS of one BODY, of which CHRIST is the HEAD. And here is the bleſſed Union and Communion in one, and here God is worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth, and as CHRIST is ſpiritual, ſo is his Body, and ſo is his Ordinances; and here are the true Chriſtians, not thoſe that onely have the Notion of thoſe things, but they that wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and poſſeſs this in Life, and they that believe hath the witneſs within themſelves, and they that believe, have paſſed from death unto life, and the life which they now live in is by faith in the Son of God, which faith is without reſpect of perſons, who are the new creatures, who are in Chriſt Jeſus, to whom there is no condemnation, who walk not after the FLESH, but after the SPIRIT,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.23.</note> for againſt ſuch there is no LAW, for they are tranſlated out of that NATURE for which the LAW was added,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168214:16"/>
and are ſet free by the Law of the Spirit of Life, and are made partakers of the <hi>Divine nature</hi> of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17.</note> by which they are made Chriſtians, and therefore ſaith <hi>Iohn, as he is ſo are we in this praſent world,</hi> and ſuch now witneſſes the effect of the blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> wrought within them, and the end of his coming, and the benefit of his <hi>Death,</hi> who are dead with him, and riſen through the death of the Croſs, and <hi>theſe are they that have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the pollutions of the world, through the knowledge of the Son of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, Chriſt within the hope of Glory,</hi> or elſe no hope of Glory, for <hi>they that cannot witneſs him ſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.23.</note> 
               <hi>are in the Reprobation,</hi> ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, and <hi>here is the Son in the Saints, and the Father in the Son,</hi> and thus are all made perfect in one, and here is the <hi>true Church,</hi> where there is but <hi>one Teacher, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one Light, one Life, and one way, one Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd and one Sheepfold, and one Prieſt over the houſhold of God, and one hope, and one language, one family, and one God and father of all;</hi> and they that cannot witneſs this, are Strangers to Chriſt, and Strangers to his Croſs, and Strangers to the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the work which the Lord now hath begun, and is carrying on <hi>by a ſtrong arm and mighty power, to redeem unto himſelfe a pure Church, and bleſſed are they that hearken unto his voyce;</hi> Here all you Formaliſts, Imitators, and ſelfe-acters are ſhut out; here all you proud ones are ſhut out; here all you luſtful ones, fleſhly ones, and carnal ones are ſhut out, and all you that are conformed like unto the world in their faſhions, in their cuſtomes, in their words, in their ways, in their worſhips and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in their love and in their fellowſhip, who are ſeeking the glory, and honor, and riches of this world, you are the children of this World, under the Dominion of the GOD of the WORLD, whoſe Kingdom is of this World: Here all you are ſhut out, who live at eaſe in your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and live want only upon the earth in the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5.5.6.</note> and the pride of life; you are the <hi>Children of Babylon, you kill the just, and he lies ſlain in the ſtreets,</hi> but here you all are ſhut out of the new Covenant of Life in the dark world, under deaths dominion, of what profeſſion and judgment ſoever, <hi>Alians and Strangers to the Covenant of Promiſe, for they that are not with us, are against us, and our union and ſociety is in the light of life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.30.</note> but you muſt all ſuffer the death of the <hi>Croſs</hi> to the life, which you now live in, before you can witneſs this Redemption; for thoſe that live with <hi>Christ</hi> are crucified with him, therefore ſo it is, they that wil take up life, muſt firſt lay down life, <hi>for the way to life is through death;</hi> therefore you muſt be ſtripped of all your old covers naked and bare, that your deceit and ſhame may appear, which you have ſo long covered with your own righteouſneſs, but now you muſt ſuffer the <hi>ſhame of the Croſs,</hi> if you would have part in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all your old <hi>wiſdome, knowledg,</hi> and <hi>notions,</hi> which you have gotten into your comprehenſions, by your conceivings of the <hi>Scripture Letter,</hi> wherin hath bin your <hi>life</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168214:16"/>
               <hi>pride,</hi> and <hi>exaltation,</hi> muſt all come to the death of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence; but I ſay unto all you Profeſſors, Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, Notioniſts and Diſputers, and Wiſe ones of this World, if you will not take up and imbrace this Croſs, Publicans and Harlots ſhall enter the Kingdome before you; therefore, not many mighty, nor many noble, nor many wiſe after the fleſh are called, but he hath choſen the fooliſh things of this world to confound the wiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>25.26.</hi> to the end.</note> and the weak to confound thoſe that are mighty, that no FLESH ſhould glory in his PRESENCE, but CHRIST is made over unto us Wiſdome, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption, that they which glory might glory in the Lord, and this I witneſs in my meaſure the things which I have ſeen, and heard, and felt, and taſted of, the good Word of Life, which was in the beginning, the ſame do I declare, and am known and read by the children of Light. And now I ſhall proceed to ſeverall paſſages that I have had with the people called Baptiſts, in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall meetings, that their deceit and deluſion may be laid open to the ſimple hearted.</p>
            <p>Upon the thirtieth day of the firſt Month called March, in the yeare 1655. I was atone <hi>Aſhens</hi> houſe in <hi>Fenſtanten,</hi> in <hi>Huntingtonſhire,</hi> where I was freely declaring the Truth of God to the people that came there to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether that day, as I was taught and moved by the Spirit of Truth, by which the holy men of God ſpoke forth the Scripture as they was moved and there came ſeverall of the people called Baptiſts into the Roome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, amongſt whom was one of their Teachers, called <hi>Richard El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligood,</hi> who after a while ſtood up in his wil and wiſdome to accuſe me, and ſaid that I ſaid that God did not reſpect any forms, and yet, ſaith he, you uſe the form, and ſo uſe that which God hath no reſpect to; but his firſt words was, Sir (if you pleaſe) I wil ſpeak ſomething to what you have ſaid; to which I made anſwer, here needs no complements, and then he runs on as aforeſaid, to which accuſation I replyed was falſe, and bid him prove what form I uſed, and he ſaid the Letter, and I replyed, he that takes the Letter to talk of without the life and power, ſuch ſets up a Form and makes a Form; but this would not ſatisfie his filthy wiſdome, which darkned his underſtanding, but becauſe I ſpoke words which are mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scripture, by the ſame ſpirit that ſpoke forth the Scripture, by which I challenge the Scripture, from him and all ſuch who have gotten it to talk of, but denies the life, and are ſtrangers to the life and power, therefore with his contrary ſpirit tasked me with a Form, which by his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick and deceitfull art would have proved, but could not, but his deceit was laid open to the people, and many declared againſt him, for a form is this, as I ſaid before, the likeneſs of a thing, but not the thing it ſelf, as they have the likeneſs of a Church, which they have imagined from the Letter, with their Elders, Paſtors, and Teachers, but not the Church it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168214:17"/>
ſelfe, and ſo they imitate the Scriptures, but live not in the life of them that ſpoke forth the Scriptures, neither are acted or guided by the ſame ſpirit that gave forth the Scriptures, and ſo wants the life and power, and thoſe are the formaliſts that makes forms and likeneſſes, to deceive the ſimple, as the devil hath the form of an Angell of Light, but not the life and power, who appears to rule in thoſe formaliſts and ſelfe-actors, but the day doth make him manifeſt, and therefore he rages: and then this <hi>Elligood</hi> denyed that I had the ſame ſpirit that gave forth the Scripture; and he ſaid the Spirit might be tryed by the Letter, for he ſaid, many falſe Spirits are entred into the world, and I asked him by what did the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle know that falſe ſpirits were gon out into the world; and he replyed and ſaid, by the Spirit of God; then I replyed and ſaid, if by the Spirit of God the Apoſtle knew that there was many falſe ſpirits gone out into the world, then by the Spirit of God he tryed falſe Spirits, and knew falſe ſpirits from the true; and here his deceit was laid open to the people, and he judged out of his own mouth to be a lyar, and to be guided by a falſe ſpirit, who would try the living by the dead; and again he ſaid, that one Spirit could not try another, for by that judgments the evil Spirits might try the good Spirits; to which I replyed, by the Spirit of God all other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are tryed, and alſo that by the Light darkneſs is diſcovered, but Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cannot comprehend the Light, neither diſcover the Light; and here again his blindneſs and ignorance, and deceit, was much diſcovered to the people, although he fed himſelf and would have ſhufled it off by his conſequences and filthy logick, but it the more laid open his deceit, and preſently the ſaid <hi>Elligood</hi> was found with another lye in his mouth, for he ſaid that I ſaid the thing ſhould be proved by every mans ſpirit, which was a very lye, for I ſaid that the baptiſme of the ſpirit was the ſubſtance of the outward baptiſme, the which he denyed and bid me prove it, and I ſaid I ſpoke to the witneſs in every mans conſcience, which his dark mind could not comprehend, but with his dark mind wreſted my words, and therefore ſaid that I ſaid it was witneſſed by every mans ſpirit, but his ſpirit was a lying-ſpirit, there tryed and made manifeſt to the people, and his blaſphemy againſt the Spirit of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20.</note> in calling truth error, and error truth, and putting Darkneſs for Light, and Light for Darkneſs, becauſe the God of the world hath blinded his eye, and many witneſſed againſt him, for his filthy Spirit was odious to many of the hearers; then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he again ſaid, that I was a deceiver, and his proofe was that I was not obedient to the command of Chriſt to be baptiſed, and I told him I was baptized, but he ſaid with water, and he ſaid that were a command of Chriſt to be baptiſed with water, and I bid him ſhow me that Scripture, but he could not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47, 48</note> but brought a Scripture in the <hi>Acts,</hi> where the Apoſtle commanded ſome to be baptiſed; and this by his filthy logick and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences he would have made a command of Chriſt, but he could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cevie the Light which did him try and make him manifeſt to the ſhame
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168214:17"/>
of his profeſſion, but he could not bring one Scripture to prove it to be a command of Chriſt to baptize with water, and then he ſhuffled to that Scripture where the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Be ye followers of us, even as we are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt,</hi> and then he ſaid Chriſt was baptiſed, but he confeſſed it was to fulfil all righteouſneſs, and I ſaid, he was alſo circumciſed, and he ſaid that was not for example, then not the Baptiſm, for both was to fulfil all righteouſneſs, to which end, he the ſubſtance came; but Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf baptiſed not with water, neither do they read that the Apoſtles was baptized with water; then who is their example? and how do they follow the Apoſtles in that, ſeeing they are baptiſed, and the Apoſtles was not; then he fled from that, being there routed, and ſaid they might be Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples before they could take up the croſs of Chriſt, and I replyed, with <hi>Christs</hi> words, that they might take up his croſs before they could be his Diſciples, which he denied, and ſaid, that wicked men upon that account might take up the croſs of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt</hi> required wicked men to take up his Croſs, and I ſaid, it was ſo, he did them require ſo to do, for by taking up his croſs they come to deny their wickedneſs, for they that bear his croſs live not in wickedneſs; but this <hi>Elligood</hi> ſaid, that wicked men could not take up his croſs, for he ſaid reproaches and outward ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings was the croſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (for his names ſake,) but this was not the croſs by which <hi>PAVL</hi> was crucified to the world, and the world to him; and ſaith <hi>PAVL,</hi> (where hee was ſpeaking concerning wickedneſs and unrighteous ones, to the <hi>Corinthians,) Such were ſome of you, but you are now cleanſed, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10, 11.</note> And here wicked ones and unrighteous ones tooke up his CROSS, which to them was the Power of GOD unto Salvation, though to the GREEKS fooliſhneſſe, and to the JEWES a ſtumbling Blocke; amongſt whom this <hi>ELLIGOOD</hi> is found, who is a Stranger to the CROSS of CHRIST, who ſaith, Reproaches and outward ſufferings is the CROSS of CHRIST, when as the CROSS of CHRIST makes Diſciples, and they muſt bee Diſciples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can ſuffer Reproaches or Perſecution for the Name of CHRIST, and muſt depart from iniquity before they bee a Prey to the World for CHRISTS ſake, for the World loves its owne, and they that take up the CROSS doe depart from iniquity, which is before Reproaches or Perſecution is ſuffered for the Name of CHRIST: And here <hi>ELLIGOOD</hi> is found the Lyar, who ſaid, Wicked men was not called to take up the Croſs of CHRIST, when as all are wicked before they take up this Croſs; and here <hi>ELLIGOOD</hi> is found to bee no Diſciple of CHRIST, who is ſuch a <hi>Stranger</hi> to the Croſs of CHRIST, who is a Lyar, and ſo are not the Diſciples of CHRIST, for the Lyar is of the DEVILL, and therefore is <hi>ELLIGOOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168214:18"/>Then I knowing him to be one of the Baptiſts Teacher, I took out ſome queries, which (not long before) I had ſent them, but no anſwer to them had I received, and I would have read them openly that the people might have heard, and alſo he that was one of their Teachers; but as I was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he not having power over his own wil could not bridle his tongue but diſorderly run into many words, ſo that the people could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and I ſpoke to him for it, and he ſaid he had not time to ſtay, and further ſaid that he was not of the ſociety of theſe Baptiſts at <hi>Fenſtanton,</hi> and yet he came with them, and from them, and then I replyed that he owned them to be the Church of God, and this he did, and then if he was not of their ſociety, he was ſhut out of the Church; and then he would have ſhufled off with his conſequences, and ſaid he dwelt far off, and then I replyed with the Apoſtles words, though abſent in body yet preſent in ſpirit, and the multitude that believed was of one heart and mind, and here was the Society of the Saints,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32.</note> and he being out of this ſociety is ſhut out of the Church, and then he would have made it have ſtood by his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, which only is to make a falſe thing ſeem true, but it the more laid open his deceitful heart, and ſhame to the hearers, who ſeverally witneſſed againſt him, to ſpeak nothing but deceit, and then ſaith he you call the Apoſtles words deceit, becauſe he had often ſtolne the Apoſtles words to make his deceit ſeem truth, by covering it with the Apoſtles words, and this is a more ſubtile deceit, and then in his wil he called me deceiver, the which he was to prove, and all the people was ſilent, and there he uttered ſeverall lies, and laid open himſelf to be the deceiver, as I had told h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, in going about to prove me a deceiver, he would the more lay open his own deceit, and prove himſelf to be the deceiver, and the people did plainly ſee it ſo, and witneſſed with me againſt him, for he did ſo utter forth his folly and deceit, that he made himſelf odious to many that was there; and at laſt he ſhufled away, under pretence he had far to go, but the judgments of God he cannot eſcape, for his damnation ſlumbreth not who is an oppoſer of the truth of God,</p>
            <p>Then there was one <hi>Phillips,</hi> an old man of the Baptiſed Party, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Roome, who in ſcorn and wrath ſtood up and ſaid they knew the firſt Principle of Religion before I was born, becauſe one of my Quaeries to them was, <hi>what is the firſt Principle of Religion?</hi> ſo I replyed to the old man if they knew it, they ſhould have anſwered, and then preſently as he was running on in many words, he ſwore as he lived and breathed, and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Sweare not at all,</hi> and here he was found not come to the firſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Religion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34.</note> but out of the Doctrine of Chirſt, and ſo hath not God, ſo I told him of his ſwearing, and he would have ſhufled it off, but he could not,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Iobn</hi> 9.</note> and I told him, <hi>He that ſeems to be Religious and brideleth not his tongue his Religion is vain,</hi> and therefore he might own his Religoin to be vain, who could not bridle his tongue, and then in his wil he ſhufled off and ſaid he would not confeſs his ſin to me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.26.</note> for I could not forgive ſin, in ſcorn
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168214:18"/>
he ſpoke, then I ſaid wo unto him that hides his ſin and covers his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but he ſhufled away in much confuſion of face, as they wil all appear, as by the Light they come to be ſearched and tryed, their coverings wil be found too narrow, and their nakedneſs will appear to their great ſhame, and confuſion of face, and they will be made to bow to the truth, and lay down their Crowns at the feet of Ieſus, for he is riſen and reigns in his Saints, to whom the Nations muſt bow, and every tongue confeſs to their condemnation who do oppoſe him, but here now by the ſingle eye, you may ſee the emptineſs of theſe forms, and what a blind hypocriſie this is of them, to waſh the outſide, but leaves the inſide full of uncleanneſs, and ſo the inſide defiles the outſide.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:168214:19"/>
            <head>A Copy of the Queries which was ſent to the Baptiſed people in Fenſtanton, with ſome more added, for them, or any whom they do concern to anſwer.</head>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="queries">
                        <head>Severall queries to you which be called Baptiſts, by your Teachers to be anſwered.</head>
                        <p>Querie 1.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>VVHat is the firſt Principle of Religion, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>VVhat is the bridle of the tongue, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="3">3. <hi>VVhat is the Church in God, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">4. <hi>VVhat is the order in the Church, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="4">5. <hi>VVhat is the Baptiſme into the Church, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. <hi>VVhether you will own the Baptiſme of the Spirit, or the Baptiſme of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and which you will deny, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith,</hi> The Baptiſme is but one? <hi>Eph.</hi> 4, 5.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. <hi>And where Chriſt ever commanded water Baptiſme.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. <hi>VVhy did the Apoſtles Baptiſe with water, and why do you baptiſe with water, and where, and when, and by what were you commanded, and where was any of the twelve Apoſtles baptiſed with water?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9. <hi>And whether you do it becauſe the Apoſtles did it, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="10">10. <hi>VVhat is the Faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="11">11. <hi>VVhether your Faith purifie your Hearts, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="12">12. <hi>And whether you commit ſin, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="13">13. <hi>How would you know there is a Chriſt but by the Scripture, and how do you witneſs the Scripture is truth?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="14">14. <hi>And what is the ground of your faith?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="13">15. <hi>VVhat is the redemption, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="16">16. <hi>VVat is the Communion of the Saints, and wherein it ſtands, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="17">17. <hi>And whether you that breaks bread do diſcern the Lords body, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="18">18. <hi>VVhat was their rule and guide that ſpoke forth the Scripture.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="19">19. <hi>VVhether you have the ſame infallible Spirit that gave forth the Scripture?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="20">20. <hi>VVhether is the Scripture your rule and guide, or the ſpirit that gave it forth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="21">
                           <pb n="33" facs="tcp:168214:19"/>21. <hi>VVhether they that are guided by the Spirit that gave it forth live not in the life thereof, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="22">22. <hi>VVhether the life of the Scripture be perfect, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="23">23. <hi>And whether you are or think to be made perfect while you are upon the earth, yea or nay? Or where do you think to be made perfect, if not upon the earth?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="24">24. <hi>And what is the life and power of godlineſs, and whether in it you dwell who have a form, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="25">25. <hi>VVhether you be waſhed and cleanſed by the blood of the Lord Ieſus and the ſpirit of our God, as the true Church was, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="26">26. <hi>VVhether you have put off the old man and put on the new, as the true Church did, yea or nay? and what is the new man?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="27">27. <hi>And whether you have put off the image of the earthly, and put on the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the heavenly, and how are they known the one from the other?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="28">28. <hi>VVhether you be not conformed like unto the world, ſo long as you follow their cuſtomes and faſhions?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="29">29. <hi>VVhether you be come that you need no man to teach you, as the true Church was, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="30">30. <hi>VVhat is the croſs whereby</hi> Paul <hi>was crucified, and whether to it you be come yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="31">31. <hi>What is the watcher that ſtrikes at the feet of the Image, and whether to it you be come, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="32">32. <hi>What is the word, and what is the death that hath paſſed over all men, even over thoſe that had not ſinned, after the ſimilitude of</hi> Adams <hi>tranſgreſſion, and whether this death you ever paſſed?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="33">33. <hi>Whether you have paſſed from death to life, yea or nay.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="34">34. <hi>Where, and when, and how received you the command and power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver any ſoul up to Satan, and where is that Satan you deliver it up to?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="35">35. <hi>What is the tree of life, and what is the tree of Knowledge, and whether upon it you do not feed, and what is the flaming ſword that is ſet to keepe from the tree of life, and whether it you ever paſſed, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="36">36. <hi>What is the beaſt which all the world wonders after and worſhips, and what is the worſhip of the beaſt, and whether any worſhips the only true God but the true church, and what is the worſhip in this church?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="37">37. <hi>What are you Miniſters of, and what do you miniſter unto, and what is the end of your miniſtry?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="38">38. <hi>And by what do you try the Spirits, and by what did the Prophets and Apoſtles try the spirits, and whether yours is the ſame tryer of Spirits as theirs was, yea or nay.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="39">39. <hi>What is the faith of the Saint, and what is the faith of the hypocrite, and how are they known the one from the other?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="40">40. <hi>How and by what was you called to the miniſtry which you profeſs?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="41">41. <hi>What is the Goſpel which you profeſs, and what is the light of the Goſpell which the infidel cannot ſee, and what is an infidel, and what is the eye which the God of the world blindes in the infidel.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="42">
                           <pb n="17" facs="tcp:168214:20"/>42. <hi>VVhat is the state and condition of the Iew inwardly, whoſe praiſe is not of man but of God, and wherein doth he differ from the Iew outwardly?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="43">43. <hi>VVhat is the new Csvenant, and where any in the New Covenant paid Tythes, and why do you cry againſt the Prieſts, and their Tythes, and their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and yet upholds them by paying them Tythes, and helping to maintain their places of worſhip, and whether this be not Babel, yea or nay?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Theſe things I do not ask becauſe I know them not, but that the Truth may be made manifeſt, and the deceit laid open, therefore anſwer by plain Scripture, or elſe all you formaliſts, imitators, and ſelfe-actors, bow unto the truth, and be ſilent, and let your mouths be ſtopped, and thereby confeſs and yeild your ſelves in an error, and to have gotten the form without the life and power, that the ſimple may no longer be deceived by you taking the ſhaddow for the ſubſtance.</p>
                        <p>Read this openly in your Church, that all may hear and anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, from him who by one of you was called a deceiver yet true, who according to the world am called,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Iames Parnel;</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>A Copy of moſt of theſe <hi>Quaeries</hi> was ſent to the chiefe Teacher of the baptiſed people in <hi>Fenstanten,</hi> and after a certain time, theſe words they ſent me back again, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A few words to him that ſaith that according to the world he is called <hi>JAMES PARNELL.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>We have received your Paper, and according to your deſire read it in the Congregation, unto which you deſire our anſwer by plain Scripture; to which we reply, that when you make good your affirmation that you are no deceiver, but true by plain Scripture, then ſhall we return you a further anſwer to your queries:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>From them who deſire to ſerve the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Iohn Denne, Edmund Male.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Then after I had received this Libel, I returned them this anſwer at the bottome of their own paper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> This is plain Scripture, though as a deceiver, yet true, and if my life and converſation doth not prove the ſame, and make good my affirmation, then in your anſwer to my queries you might have taxed me, and proved to the contrary; but this of you is but a plain ſhufle to blind the world, and ſhun the ſhame, and ſtill to blind the people who are enſlaved under your deceit, but this wil the more manifeſt your ignoranre; then not long after they returned me this anſwer as followeth.</p>
            <p>It is not plain Scripture, though as a deceiver yet true, as deceivers and yet true, is plain Scripture, the greateſt deceiver in the world might as wel brought it to prove himſelf no deceiver, but true as wel as you, for your converſation we know it not, we have not to ſay to that, but this we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168214:20"/>
know, that wolves may come in ſheeps cloathing, and this doth appear in you, in drawing people from the truth, as namely, from Water-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme which is a command of the Lord unto believers; as for your ſaying we might have taxed you in our anſwer to your queries, we think you might plainly ſee your folly in this, you affirmed nothing in them as your judgment, how ſhould we then tax you and prove the contrary? and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, we made no promiſe to anſwer, and therefore you might have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your daring and falſe words, to ſay the people are enſlaved under our deceit, and therefore until you have made good what you have taken in hand by plain Scripture by the fruit of your lips, by bringing the Doctrine of Chriſt, and owning his Commandments, we ſay untill then, we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to let you alone, let them alone, they be blind leaders of the blind, you having been ſo plainly manifeſt unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Here all people who with a ſingle eye reads, may ſee the deceit of this people, for I ſpoke but of one, and therefore in that reſpect it is plain Scripture, <hi>though as v deceiver yet true,</hi> but theſe are they, who if they could, would make a make a man an offender for a word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.21.</note> my converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they cannot touch, and yet are not aſhamed to ſay, the greateſt decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver might as wel have brought this Scripture as I, and this is the blindneſs of their mindes; and alſo ſay (becauſe I deny water-baptiſme to be an Ordinance or a Command of Chriſt) that I am a woolf in ſheeps cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which they do affirm to be a command, but cannot prove it, and ſo are ſuch as uſe their tongues, and ſay the Lord ſaith, when he never ſpoke to them, but ſurely a woolf in ſheeps cloathing is to be known by the life and practiſe, but in this they are blind and cannot diſcern, and ſo themſelves are the blind leaders of the blind, but I ſhall not let you alone but make you manifeſt unto the world, neither did Chriſt let them alone but pronounced woes, and declared againſt them; and here I am ſure you might ſee your folly, who ſay I have been ſo manifeſt unto you, and ſaid, you know not my converſation, what a confuſion is this, but it is your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers language and alſo in expecting me to affirm my judgment upon my own queries, then what need I ſend them to you to anſwe if I anſwer them my ſelf; and here I am ſure you might ſee your own folly, for it is here plainly plainly laid open, ſo that all who are led by you, are plainly ſeen to be enſlaved under your deceit, and theſe words ſhall ſtand for truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, which you call falſe, who are the blind, and ſo put evill for good, and good for evil: and the Doctrine of Chriſt I have brought, and his commandments I do own, from and againſt you, who are the buſie-bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſelfe-actors, who have nought to do with him nor his commands, therefore ſilence deceivers, for here I have made good what I have taken in hand, which witneſſed ſhall be in your condemnation.</p>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:168214:21"/>
               <head>The occation of another meeting betwixt the people called Baptiſts and the people called Quakers.</head>
               <p>SEverall times when I have come to the Town of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I have heard a rumour of a boaſting and daring, that ſprung from the people called Baptiſts, behind my back concerning a diſpute with me, yet I had received nothing from them, neither by word nor writing, to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of their mindes, therefore I being in the Town ſent them word that I heard a voyce of ſuch a thing, but knew not the certainty, therefore to let me know their mindes in writing, if they intended ſuch a thing; ſo then one <hi>Hindes</hi> a Tanner in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ſent me this Note as followeth, which <hi>Ioſeph Doughty</hi> had ſent unto him.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="note">
                           <head>The Note.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Brother</hi> Hind, <hi>as touching a Diſcourſe with</hi> James Parnel, <hi>I ſhall be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do God and men ſervice in it, to my power given to me.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Frſt, Provided that it be ſomewhat publike; the queſtions in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie may be ſtated in writing.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. That the queſtions may be ſuch as may be reſolved and anſwered according to Scripture.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. That the queſtions agreed upon, may be delivered into the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants hands, three dayes before the day of diſpute.</p>
                           <p n="4">4 That to avoid confuſion in multitude of words, a ſhort form of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſhall be uſed on both parts.</p>
                           <p n="5">5. That ſome ſhall be choſen on both ſides, to ſee order on both ſides obſerved in diſcourſe, and competent Judges alſo appointed.</p>
                           <p n="6">6. That cenſorious raſh terms of judging, ſhall not be uſed.</p>
                           <p n="7">7. That the diſputants ſhal declare before the people their intent in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, Aprill this 17. 1655.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Ioſeph Doughty.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                        <div type="reply">
                           <head>My reply to this was as followeth, as not being willing to come under their ſnares.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Rep.</hi> This is not to me, but betwixt Brother and Brother, ſo if you two Brothers are agreed concerning this your intent towards me, let me know your mind in writing now while I am in the Town, for while I was abroad there was a voyce of ſuch a thing as from you, but to me you did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare your mindes, neither in word nor writing, therefore now I am in the Town, let me know your mindes in writing, that there may be no boaſting nor daring in ſecret, for truth is bold and ſeeks no covers, this from me to you I ſend, and do require your anſwer, who am called,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>I. P.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This was writ on the back-ſide of their note and ſent back to <hi>Hindes,</hi> who forthwith flew into a great rage againſt the meſſenger in the ſtreete, and ſaid that I lyed in ſaying that the note was not to me, which any one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:168214:21"/>
who can read, may plainly ſee it ſo, and him to be the Lyar for the Lake, and his ſeeming Religion to be vain, who is ſtill in old <hi>Cain's</hi> nature, in wrath and bitterneſs, without a bridle to the tongue. Then the next morning I received this from them as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="note">
                           <p>
                              <hi>Iames Parnel,</hi> this is to thee, my intent towards thee is this, If thou art minded to diſpute with me, appoint time and place publike, and if the Lord will, I will diſpute with thee, and ſo on with his proviſo's as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="reply">
                           <head>Then my Reply was as followeth.</head>
                           <p>To thee <hi>Ioſeph Doughty,</hi> I do reply, That thou muſt underſtand the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this Diſpute to be ſprung from thee or thy party, as I did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare on the backſide of thy other paper, ſo if thou, or any of you, that made your boaſts or darings behind my back, or have any thing againſt me or the truth, which I bear teſtimony unto, or the way which I walke in, I am ready now at all times through the power of God, to ſtand up for, and defend the ſame, againſt thee or any other, who ſhall object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, oppoſe, or gainſay it, be it in the Towns-hall, or as publike as you will, and what I have at any time declared againſt you people, or your profeſſion, I ſhall be ready to maintain, and juſtifie, by ſuch weapons as I have, which are not carnal, but ſpiritual, and here is time and place from me declared; but to the end of all Diſputes and Arguments I am come, for before they was I am, and in the Light do them comprehend, and judge to be out of the Light in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Diſputer and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of this World: but ſtil I ſay againſt ſuch I ſtand a Witneſs for the truth which I have received of God, and by his power am carried abroad, to declare and preach abroad, to the directing and turning people minds to the true Light of the Lord Jeſus, and there to come into the love and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, where lives the Children of Light, the end of all Diſputes and Arguments, and this I am ready to defend and ſeal with my blood; but I ſay my weapons are not carnal, but ſpiritual, and as for theſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoes of thine, they are rather for me to lay upon thee, according to equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for I am the defender, but theſe things of thee I do not require, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three dayes before hand, but am ready at any time to ſtand to what I, have here declared, and as for confuſion in multitude of words, which is thy fourth Proviſo,</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Reply.</hi> Look thou to that on thy part, and if thou canſt tax mee thou mayeſt.</p>
                           <p>And as for order in the diſcourſe, for which thou would have ſome choſen, which is thy fifth proviſo.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Reply.</hi> Look thou to that on thy part; for my God is a God of Order, and if thou canſt tax me thou mayeſt, and let that ſtand againſt me; but if there be men of power, to keep the people of the world in order I am not againſt it.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="38" facs="tcp:168214:22"/>And as for competent Judges which thou would have appointed:</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Reply.</hi> Is the <hi>Scripture</hi> thy rule, and not thy judg, but thou muſt flee from that to the judgment of man, which is changeable, or elſe how comes Diſputes and controverſies? but to that judgment I ſhall not ſtand, the ſpiritual man ſhal be the competent judge, and the Scripture ſhall witneſs.</p>
                           <p>And as for cenſorious raſh terms of judging, which is thy ſixth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Reply.</hi> Look thou to that on thy part, and if my judgment thou canſt finde contrary to Scripture, thou mayeſt by Scrpture diſprove it; but what is that, that would not be judged?</p>
                           <p>And as for declaring before the people the intent and purpoſe in diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which is thy ſeventh proviſo.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Reply.</hi> If thou who art the Diſputant amengſt the people, haſt any thing to ſay unto the People, thou mayeſt declare thy mind according to the freedome of thy minde, I ſhall not bind thee, neither ſhal I by thee be bound, but as the Lord puts into my mouth, I ſhal declare unto the people, what is my minde and intent, as his ſpirit guides me; ſo that for that I take no thought.</p>
                           <p>So here I have declared my mind in Reply unto thy writing, where thou may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſt underſtand my minde, if thou haſt an ear to hear, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding open, and if this do not ſatisfie thee, and the reſt of you, yet nevertheleſs ceaſe your boaſting and daring behind the back for the time to come; and let this witneſs for me to any honeſt heart, whether it be not fair and equal, and ſo I reſt in the unchangeable,</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>I. P.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>So it ſeems this pleaſed them, and ſo it was concluded to be of the twentieth day, called Fryday, of the ſecond moneth, called <hi>April,</hi> ſo when the hour came which was appointed, we was diſappointed of the meeting-place which the Baptiſts had provided; for they ſent me word they had provided a place, but when we came to meet it could not be had, and ſo we was diſappointed; then we was in this <hi>Hind's</hi> houſe, and the woman of the houſe much fumed and raged at us all the while we was in the houſe, which manifeſted what ſpirit ſhe was of, and that water had availed her nothing, for ſhe was nothing departed from the old nature: ſo then they would have had us to have met in the yard, but there could bee no order for multitude of rude people, and bruitiſh Schollars, which was as unta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med bruit beaſts,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32.</note> like the beaſts at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> fought with after the manner of men; ſo I paſſed to a friends houſe hard by, and there continued declaring the truth, as I was moved to the people, and there the idle drones followed, even <hi>Babylons Children,</hi> with their turbulent vain contending ſpirits, oppoſing and gainſaying the truth, like <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> their fore-fathers, who muſt periſh in the gainſaying of <hi>Core:</hi> ſo then word came that the Baptiſts was in the Shire-houſe in the Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:168214:22"/>
and had ſent for me, and ſo I went up thither, and when I came there the Goaler diſcharged me for ſtaying there, and ſaid I cauſed tumults, though I had not ſpoken any thing to the people whereby to cauſe a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult; but the generation of this world was alwayes tumultuous, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Chriſt and his Apoſtles, though they were known to be innocent and harmleſs, offering violence to none, yet it was ſo with them then, and it is ſo now with the ſame ſeed, where it is born up to rule, becauſe it is not of the world, but hated of the world, for the enmity lodgeth in the world, the world is the ſea, with its tumultuous gathering together of the raging roaring waves, caſtnig up mire and dirt, foaming out its own ſhame: and though an innocent perſon travel here, he muſt ſuch diſtractions expect, and tumults of raging waves about him, caſting up ſuch as they have; but he that made the bounds of the ſea, can and doth deliver his out of the compaſs of its bounds, and then it cannot paſs its bounds, for its bounds it keeps; here is a parable hid from the wiſdome of the world, but the ſame which gave it forth, the ſame wil open it to the unlearned.</p>
               <p>Then after the Goaler had ſpoke to me, they made ſome way for me to come up to the Baptiſts, who was there ſitting upon the bench like Judges; this <hi>Doughty</hi> and one <hi>Rix</hi> a brewer, an old Phariſee in Cambridge, the one a baptiſt, and the other of the Independant ſect ſo called, but two great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies one again another, in oppoſition againſt each ſect, yet theſe two was joyned together as friends againſt me, and thus ſate <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> together like judges againſt the innocent, ſo when I was gotten amongſt the people, I would not meddle until the Goaler had given freedome for me to ſtay there, as he had before diſcharged me; ſo after a while he gave leave, ſo that we would be ſhort, then this <hi>Doughty</hi> the baptiſt, ſo called, ſtood up and put off his hat to the people, after the manner of the heathen with a complement, pleading of the ſhortneſs of the time, and ſo begun with a queſtion, ſo I ſaid his queſtion might ſtand, and as he had liberty to ſpeak to the people, ſo would I, and then he would have hindred me, contrary to what was before agreed upon betwixt us by the paſſages afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſo I got liberty to ſpeak ſomething to the people, and declared what I was made a miniſter of, according to the wil of God, and then I took out a paper and read unto the people the occaſion of my comming thither to meet the baptiſts that day, and by the concluſions therein I was to have liberty to ſpeak my mind as wel as he, and he was to accuſe me before the people, or the truth which I bore teſtimony unto, but he broke his firſt agreement and flew to queſtion, ſo then to ſatisfie the ſimple hearted, I gave this anſwer to the underſtanding of the ſimple.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Baptiſts queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> The writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles which are called Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whether are they the words and ſayings of the moſt high God, yea, or nay.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:168214:23"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Word of God, which is God, which dwelt in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles, from it they ſpoke forth the things which is recorded in Scripture, but this would not ſatisfie the Baptiſts, but cryed out no anſwer, and <hi>Doughty</hi> ſtood up, and put off his hat, and beckoned to the young Prieſts and Schollars, and ſaid, Judg ye Gentlemen of Divinity, &amp; there was one <hi>Anger,</hi> a drunken Prieſt, ſided with the Baptiſts; now let all ſee how contrary to their own principles they acted; but ſome of the Schollars had ſo much underſtanding as to receive it for an anſwer, but the drunkards ſided with the Baptiſts, and the ruder ſort, who could not underſtand, though there was many ſimple hearts that with this anſwer was ſatisfied, but the wiſe muſt be catched in their own craftineſs, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times I repeated this anſwer over to the people, but the Baptiſt and his party could not receive it, becauſe it was in the groſs to their wiſdome; but there was that which I ſpoke to, which could and did receive it; then <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Doughty</hi> the Baptiſt, and <hi>Henry Rix</hi> the old Phariſee, joyned together, and with one conſent ſaid I durſt not anſwer it; and thus the unclean ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits joyned together, and made lies their refuge; and after that I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating my anſwer over to the people, <hi>Doughty</hi> ſtood up, and ſaid, I ſpoke I knew not what, and then I taxed him with a lie, and then hee ſaid it was not to his queſtion, but I bid him prove that I ſpoke I knew not what, but he could not, but ſhuffled off, and ſaid I would flie from his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and there he ſtood; then the Goaler called to depart, and <hi>Doughty</hi> ſtood up and ſpoke to the Goaler, not to ſuffer me to ſtay after him, leaſt I ſhould ſeduce the people; there I ſtood up, and challenged him to prove me a ſeducer to the people, but hee had noting to ſay for that, but manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe to be a ſeducer, and a ſlanderer, and a reproacher of the truth of God, and ſo muſt take part with his fore-fathers of the wrath of God; then I openly ſpoke to the people, that if any there could tax me, or lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to my charge, I was there to anſwer, but none did or could there accuſe me: ſo then I paſſed into the Caſtle-yard, then the wilde bruitiſh Schollars who had plotted together (as I was after informed) to abuſe me, and they flocked together about me like the wilde beaſts of the Forreſt, &amp; there I was toſſed as amongſt the raging waves of the Sea, to and fro, and at laſt was hurried into a houſe, where I got ſhut of thoſe Caterpillars, which the Nation ſwarms with, but the baptiſed party paſſed away without diſturbance, ſo it appears <hi>the world loves its own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh <hi>Cambridge!</hi> is this the fruits of thy Miniſtry, which thou haſt ſo long profeſſed, which hath been ſo long preached in thee? is this thy Divinity, and is theſe thy preachers of Divinity? nay, they are now found out (by the light of God) to be the Diviners and Sorcerers, Witches and Magicians, that are onely oppoſers and gainſayers of the truth, who muſt periſh in the gain-ſaying of <hi>Core,</hi> they are known by their fruits, and the fruits of their Miniſtry, and thy Wel-head of Divinity is now found
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168214:23"/>
the Well-head of Sorcery, witchcraft and ſpiritual whoredome,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.11.</note> and all abomination, and uncleanneſs, the day doth declare it, and one Fountain cannot bring forth both bitter water and freſh. Oh! Antichriſt hath reigned long over poor inſlaved captivated ſouls; but now <hi>Iſraels Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hath appeared, and the Son of Righteouſneſs is riſen with healing in his wings, and Antichriſts Kingdome is come, and coming to an end,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and Chriſt himſelfe will reign, and rule in truth and in righteouſneſs in his ranſomed ones, and this is the mighty King, and Redeemer of Iſrael out of captivity, into a Land of peace, and love and unity, where the ranſomed ones do dwell with their Captain and their King, who doth deliver his owne Lambs out of the mouths of raging wolfs and dogs; Praiſes, Praiſes everlaſting, eternal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 01.16.</note> 
                  <hi>to the everlasting God of Life for ever: and thus we are ſent as ſheep amongst wolves, but in the power of the Almighty we are ſent forth, and the arm of the Almighty is with us, and doth deliver us from being a prey to the Lyons whelps which would us devoure, and bleſſed are all they that receive our teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, it is Peace and ſalvation to their ſouls: Now where is the VViſe?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>where is the Scribe? where is the Diſputer of this world? Hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdome of this world, and hath choſen the fooliſh things to confound the wiſe, and the weak to confound thoſe that are mighty, that no Fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence?</hi> Unto this <hi>Doughty</hi> I ſent ſeveral of theſe queries which are before mentioned, but I received no anſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Another Meeting betwixt the people called Baptiſts, and the people called QVAKERS.</head>
               <p>UPpon the fourth day of the third month called <hi>May,</hi> wee was ſeveral of the Lords people, met together in a friends Orchard at Litle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in the Iſle of <hi>Elie,</hi> and there came in three of the Tachers of the baptiſed people, the chief of them was one <hi>Iohn Ray</hi> of Wickombruck in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and he came (as he ſaid) with a meſſage, and that was to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate two perſons that was there, namely, <hi>Samuel Cater,</hi> and <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel Cater</hi> (who had formerly been Elders amongſt them) out of their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, whenas they was come out of their ſociety before, and owned the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and denied their form and ſhadow, without their caſting out; but thou <hi>Ray</hi> to uphold thy form, did there diſorderly run into words in thy own wil, and then went away, and would not ſtay to prove what thou had done, but ſaid, thou was to be at the Steeplehouſe ſhortly: ſo as I was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I ſpoke unto the people there preſent, and after a while when I had ſpoken what was given me of the Lord to ſpeak, I paſſed into the town, and there I hearing how the Baptiſt was railing on the truth in the Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, I paſſed to the Steeplehouſe with ſome friends that had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſociety been of their ſociety, and when I came there, I found thee <hi>Iohn Ray</hi> ſet up in the ſeat of the Phariſee, the chiefeſt place in the ASSEMBLY, ſpeaking a Divination of thy owne braine,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:168214:24"/>
and not from the mouth of the Lord, as thou confeſſed openly amongſt the people, that none in theſe dayes had any open viſion, or heard God ſpeak immediately, and here thou waſt an open lyar amongſt the people, but here thou barred thy ſelf from the ſame Spirit that ſpoke in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, and therefore art a deceiver, for he that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt is none of his, and ſo thou meaſured others by thy ſelf, but I and hundreds more of the Children of light,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</note> do witneſs thee to be a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar and deceiver in theſe dayes, who comes not in the name of the Lord, but in thy own name, therefore the world receives thee, but here out of thy own mouth thou art judged and condemned out of the new Covenant, for there God himſelf is teacher, and thou that never heard him ſpeak imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.45.</note> and yet comes to preach his word, thou art a ſtranger unto God, and a blind guide, a deceiver, and a falſe Prophet, who runs and the Lord ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſent thee, therefore thou profits not the people at all, but art a thiefe, and ſteals the words of the Prophets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and adds a divination of thy own Braine, and ſo feeds the people with notions, and ayry knowledg,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.14.</note> and caſting the Childrens bread unto dogs, but the greater is thy condemnation, who for a pretence makes longs prayers, and wreſts and perverts the Scripture to thy own deſtruction, but think not that thou ſhalt be heard for thy much babling, for the hand of the Lord is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee.</p>
               <p>And there in the ſeat of the Phariſee thou <hi>Ray</hi> had taken a text of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles words, and added thy own meanings, uſes, applications, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, thou merchant of Babylon, and diviner, where haſt thou any ſuch example from the Prophets or Apoſtles,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.8.</note> they ſpoke from the mouth of the Lord, and as they was moved by the Holy Ghoſt, and as the Spirit gave them utterance, and they ſpoke with power and authority, and not as the Scribes, but thou doſt ſpeak in the wiſdome of the World, like as the Scribes and Phariſes, and Prieſts, amongſt whom I number thee, and here thou art ſhut from the Apoſtles and their practiſe, with thy carnall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, uſes, applications, and divinations; and this was thy text which thou had ſtoln out of the Apoſtles writings, which was writ unto the church and thou applyed them unto the world and ſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Text.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.0, 21, 22.</note> For if after they have eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped the polutions of the world through the knowledg of the Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, they are again intangled therein and overcome, the latter end is worſe than the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and from this thou raiſed thy Uſes, Applications, and dark Meanings, whenas neither thou nor any there which belonged to thee, or owned thee, that had ever eſcaped the polu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world, or ever had come to the knowledg of Chriſt, but are ſtil in darkneſs and blindneſs, in their ſins and corruptions, in covetouſneſs in pride, and wantonneſs, in lightneſs, in wrath, and in anger, and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs, in back-biting, in ſlandering, and falſe accuſing, in railing and curſed ſpeaking, in lying, and blaſpheming, only it may be have paſſed through the water,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</note> but it is not the waſhing away the filth of the fleſh, but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:168214:24"/>
here both thou and they are ſtil, and theſe are the polutions of the world, but they that know and witneſs Ieſus Chriſt come in the fleſh, witneſs the waſhing away thoſe ſins and polutions; and thus thou wreſts and perverts the Scripture to thy own deſtruction, and then thou went on dreaming and flattering, and daubing up the people with untempred morter, ſaying the Lord ſaith when he never ſpoke to thee, and then thou run on rayling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the back of people that was not there, as thou often ſaid, thou ſpoke it of none there; and thus thou uttered forth thy folly, and it is like thou might be-lie thoſe whom thou ſpoke of, for I heard the utter forth many open lies, and then thou run on to thy water baptiſme, to maintain it an Ordinance of Chriſt, and thou brought this Scripture in the ſix of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, which the Apoſtle ſpoke to the Church;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Know you not that ſo many of you as were baptiſed into Ieſus Chriſt, was baptiſed into his death;</hi> thou blind hypocrite, was this water baptiſme, they that are in Chriſt are new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſo are not thoſe who are baptiſed with water, but they are in the ſame nature as they was before; and thou mayeſt read in <hi>Corinthians</hi> the twelf, what baptiſme that was he ſpoke of there, for ſaith he, by one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are we all baptiſed into one body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and they that are thus baptiſed, are baptiſed into Chriſt, but as I ſaid before, it is not the waſhing away the filth of the fleſh; and here is thy folly and ignorance laid open, who art ſo blind as to bring this Scripture to prove water baptiſme to be an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt, and again it ſaith they was baptiſed into his death, and in the ſame Chapter it ſaith, <hi>they that are dead are freed from ſin,</hi> and this thou denyed that any could be ſet free from ſin ſo long as they are upon the earth; &amp; thus thou denies Jeſus Chriſt &amp; his ordinances, who came to take away ſin, &amp; to clenſe his people from thier ſin, but praiſed be the Lord we do witneſs a freedom from ſin by Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Lamb of God, who came to take away the ſin of the world; &amp; to redem his peope from their ſin, and to redeme unto himſelf a pure Church, not having ſpot or wrinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, or any ſuch thing, and ſaith he if the Son have ſet you free, then are you free indeed; and here is the liberty of the Sons of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.36. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1.</note> and now are we the Sons of God, and now they that witneſs this and confeſs it, ſuch blind hypocrites as thou, calls them blaſphemers, and ſo denies Jeſus Chriſt come in the fleſh, and ſo are of Antichriſt, and one while thou affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in thy Pulpet that they that preſſed and led people into holineſs, was no deceivers, but they that led them into ſin and evil was deceivers, and then afterward told the people they never could be free from ſin, ſo long as they are upon the earth; and thus thou would ſettle them upon the lees, and deny Jeſus Chriſt come in the fleſh, who comes to clenſe from all ſin, and thus art thou judged out of thy own mouth for a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>And thou alſo brought this Scripture to maintain water baptiſm, where the Apoſtle ſaid, for as many of you as have been baptiſed unto Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.</note>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:168214:25"/>
have put on Chriſt, now let any whoſe underſtandings are enlightned by the Light of Chriſt, read this Scripture and ſee if this mention water bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and if any by water baptiſme do now put on Chriſt, and by the Light judge thee to be a Lyar and a deceiver, and a perverter of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to thy own deſtruction, and all who believes thee except you repent, and then thou run on to prove the Letter to be the word, by way of deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe that ſay that God is the word, and that there is no written word, when the Letter ſaith it ſelf, that the word is God; and then thou brought this Scripture to prove the Letter to be the Word, in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Being born again, not of corruptible ſeed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth and abideth for ever; for all fleſh is graſs, and the glory of man as the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of graſs, the graſs withereth and the flower fadeth away, but the word of the Lord endureth for ever,</hi> and this is the word which by the Goſpel is preached unto you; here thou dark ſot, thy blindneſs and ignorance is more laid open; is the letter immortal, or any written word immortal, or liveth or abideth for ever? or is any born again but of God, and is not he that ſame immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal word which the Scripture often bears teſtimony unto, and alſo in this place,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and Chriſt the Lamb of God is the everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> who preached the word, and his Apoſtles was made clean through the word which he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto them, but this was not the dead Letter, in the which thou would find life,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39.</note> and ſo art ſeeking the living amongſt the dead, like the blinde Phariſe, who thought in the Scripture to find eternall life, but would not come unto Chriſt that they might have life; and here thou art in their ſteps, though thou made light of this Scripture, and ſaid that ſome added yee to it, and ſaid, ye ſearch the Scripture, for in them ye think to have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, they are they that teſtifie of me, but ye wil not come unto me that ye might have life, this was ſpoken by Chriſt unto the Phariſes, who could not believe that he was the Chriſt, but thought in the Scriptures to find eternal life, but would not come unto Chriſt that they might have life, and therefore he bid them ſearch the Scripture, for there the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had propheſied of him, and thereby they might know that he was the Chriſt, if they had ſearched with the ſingle eye, therefore without yee, I ſay unto thee, ſearch the Scriptures, for they are they that beare teſtimony of Chriſt to be the word, and all that do ſearch the Scripture with a ſingle eye wil find Chriſt to be the word and wil believe it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.24.</note> and not be ſo blind as to put the Letter for the Word, as thou doſt, who brought another Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with thy dark mind, where the Apoſtle ſaith, ye have a more ſure word of Propheſie the which ye do wel to take heed unto, as to a light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in a dark place until the day dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in your hearts, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20.</note>Here thou ſtil the more manifeſts thy blindneſs, who puts darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, and ſo art under the wo from the Lord, who puts the Letter for the light, how doth the Letter ſhine, and what dark place doth it ſhine in as a Light? here the ignorant may ſee thy folly; and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:168214:25"/>
thus thou art a Stranger to the Light of Chriſt, which dwelt in the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and the word is nigh in the heart and in the mouth,<note place="margin">Rom.</note> to which thou ſheweſt thy ſelf a Stranger, who drawes peoples mindes from this word in their hearts, to the Letter without, putting that for the word, and ſo art a blinde guide and a deceiver, who cryes, Lo, here without in the Letter, when the Apoſtle ſaith, Go not forth, the Word is nigh in the heart: And thus thou oppoſes the Apoſtle, and draws from his Doctrine, and brings another Doctrine, and ſo art not to be received,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.</note> but held as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, as thou art, by the children of Light, and ſometimes thou called the Letter the Word, and ſometimes a Story, and here was thy confuſion; and then thou run on with thy fauning diſſembling Speeches, making a ſhew oftentimes to the people of ſpeaking more of a matter, but for wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their patience. Oh bluſh and be aſhamed of thy Doctrine! now thou makes it appear what filthy ſtuff it is, that art afraid it ſhould weary peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples patience to hear it, if it was of God it would not be weariſome to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of God to hear it, but it was not of God, therefore I am ſure it was weariſome and burdenſome to the Spirit of God: and here thou art ſhut out with thy frothy Stuff and vain Complements, to be a deceiver: and then thou ſaid, <hi>If you pleaſe, I will ſpeak more,</hi> and thus thou markes out thy ſelfe for a Man-pleaſer, and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>If I yet pleaſed men, I ſhould not be a ſervant of Chriſt.</hi> Now read thy ſelf where thou art,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note> who art yet a man-pleaſer, who comes with ſuch inticing words of mens wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo that the Preaching of the CROSS to thee is fooliſhneſs, and the Prophets who had the Spirit of the LORD, and the Word of the LORD, they ſpoke, <hi>whether they would heare, or forbeare,</hi> and here thou art ſhut out both from the Spirit of GOD, and the Word of GOD, which is one, who art a Man-pleaſer, and if not a Servant of CHRIST, then a Servant of the DEVILL, and ſo I marke thee out, that all may know thee, and no longer bee deceived by thee with the ſhadow inſtead of the ſubſtance, with thy inticing words of Mens wiſdome; and thou told the people thou ſpoke to the Reaſon of Man, when as all men in the fall their Reaſon is corrupted, and the naturall Man receives not the things of GOD,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.14.</note> for Man by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is worſe then a Beaſt, and there art thou, who art preaching to the corrupt Reaſon of MAN in the FALL, to judge of thy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſtuffe, for I know there was none there that owned thee, but ſuch like; but the Meſſage of <hi>PAVL</hi> was to turne Peoples mindes from Darkneſs to Light, but thou ſtrive to draw Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples mindes from the Light within,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18.</note> to the Dead LETTER without them, telling them, that was the LIGHT, and that was the WORD, and ſo thou bewitched them with thy Lying Divinations, and bid them ſearch that, and read often that, and cleave unto that; but I ſay, they that read that, and not by the light within them, read a parable, and it is unto them as a book ſealed, though they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168214:26"/>
may by their carnall wiſdome add their own meanings, but that muſt be ſhut out of the Scripture,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</note> for ſuch are unlearned and unfruitfull in the word, and ſo wreſts the Scripture to their own deſtruction, but by this know, that I go not about to draw men from reading the Scripture; ſo that they read with this ſingle eye, the Light which gave it forth, ſo ſhal they that read underſtand, but to thee this is a myſtery, and therefore thou went about to deny Chriſt in man, and God in man, by way of deriſion to thoſe that witneſſed forth Chriſt within, God within, &amp; thou ſaith that he meant he was in them by his words, and thou brought this Scripture, <hi>if you abide in me and my words abide in you, ye ſhall ask what you will, and it ſhall be done unto you;</hi> in this place (thou Serpent) he meant as he ſpoke, but <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed Chriſt within, and ſaid, <hi>They that could not witneſs Christ within was Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,</hi> and ſo art thou, who denies Chriſt come in the fleſh, and <hi>Paul</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>Christ within the hope of glory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>the miniſtry which had been hid,</hi> and ſo it ſeems is ſtil from thee, therefore to thee this preaching is fooliſhneſs, and as fancies, and whimſies, but unto us that are ſaved, <hi>Chriſt the power of God and the wiſdome of God,</hi> by which thy folly and thy ignorance of Chriſt is here made manifeſt, and that thou never eſcaped the polutions of the world by the knowledg of Chriſt, who denies him, as he is known to all who have eſcaped the polutions of the world by the knowledg of him, and they that thus know him not,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Coo.</hi> 13.5.</note> are in the reprobation; &amp; here art thou a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Antichriſt, who denies Chriſt come in the fleſh; and then thou went on with thy deluding ſpirit, preſſing the wicked to pray, yea there was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there preſent of the people of the world beſides thy own company, whom both thou and thy company counts as heathen, yet thou preſſed them much to pray, and to take unto them words and pray, whenas the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>The prayers of the wicked are abominable;</hi> and thus thou did that which was abominable in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.8.</note> in praying thy ſelf, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the wicked to pray, and to ſteal other mens words and pray, for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you nor they have any words but what you ſteal out of the Scripture, for thou haſt ſhut thy ſelf from that by which the Apoſtles preached, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou thus runs into confuſion, and thou told the people of deceivers, and nominated them to be ſuch as denyed Baptiſme and Ordinances of Chriſt, and the Scripture, and the Reſurrection of the Dead, and eternall judgment: ſo when thou had done thy divination and thy formal prayer, I ſtood up and claimed the order of the true Church, that all might ſpeak one by one, and if any thing was revealed to him that ſtands by, let the firſt hold his peace, and then like <hi>Cain</hi> thy countenance fel, thou being ſtruck with guilt in thy conſcience,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30, 31</note> and fear ſurpriſed the heart of the hypocrite and thou was ſhufling away, but I bid the ſtand, for, ſaid I, thou art a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, as I ſhall prove the one before all the people, therefore ſtand to maintain what thou haſt ſaid, but ſaid I unto the people, the Prophets and Apoſtles, and the holy men of God who ſpoke forth the Scriptures, they ſpoke from the infallible ſpirit of God, as they was acted, guided, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:168214:26"/>
thereby, but all who comes with their words, and pretending to preach and not from the ſame infallible Spirit, ſuch are deceivers, of which this man is one, who ſtands here in the ſeat of the Phariſee, and he being ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with guilt, fetled to be gone, and ſeveral would have ſtopped him, but he ſaid he would be gone, unleſe they kept him in by violence, and I ſaid unto the people, know this, that theſe things wherewith he marks out <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers</hi> I own, ſo that I am none of thoſe, for the Scripture I own, and the true <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> I own, &amp; the <hi>Reſurrection from the Dead</hi> I own, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>judgment</hi> upon the <hi>wicked</hi> I own, ſo that I am none of thoſe which he marked out, but this man is a deceiver, and ſo I ſhall prove him if he will ſtay, but thou <hi>Ray</hi> was aſhamed of thy <hi>Ministry,</hi> and durſt not ſtand to what thou had ſaid, but plainly like a hireling fled from thy ſtage, and left thy <hi>Flock</hi> like a <hi>cowardly Serpent,</hi> I never knew Baptiſt ſo routed out of a Pulpet; but the <hi>Independants</hi> joyned with him, and the <hi>Priests rude multitude</hi> ſtood up for him, and ſeveral would have been perſecuting of me, but by the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>God</hi> I was preſerved and kept from the hands of ſuch unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men; but thus did all <hi>Sects</hi> ever joyn againſt the one ſingle <hi>Truth,</hi> but it is but that the Scripture ſhould be fulfilled,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3, 1, 2, 3.</note> that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhould joyne in <hi>Battel</hi> againſt the <hi>Lamb,</hi> but the <hi>Lamb</hi> ſhall overcome, and they ſhall lay down their <hi>Crowns</hi> before <hi>Him,</hi> and his <hi>Enemies</hi> ſhall become his <hi>Foot-ſtoole,</hi> and he wil tread them in the wine-preſs alone without the <hi>City,</hi> therefore tremble all you <hi>Formaliſts, Imitators</hi> and <hi>Selfe-actors,</hi> who have gotten a <hi>Form</hi> but deny the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> even <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> whom you have crucified, which you ſhall be made to confeſs with <hi>weeping tears,</hi> where your eyes behold him whom you have pierced.</p>
               <p>So after I had paſſed out of the <hi>Steeple-houſe,</hi> when the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was put to the rout, I ſtood upon a <hi>Grave</hi> in the <hi>Grave-yard,</hi> and there I called to the <hi>people,</hi> if any of them had any thing to object againſt me I was there to maintain and ſtand up for the truth, to the which I had openly born te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony in their <hi>Town</hi> but none would come to my face; and there was one <hi>Captain Cole</hi> there preſent, who had been counted an Independant <hi>Teacher,</hi> until his flock forſook him and owned the <hi>Truth,</hi> and he had railed againſt the <hi>Truth</hi> behind my back, but he would not come then and ſpeak to my face, and ſince he hath impriſoned one of his <hi>neighbours Sonne</hi> for obeying the command of God, and coming to his Houſe for a ſigne: ſo I ſpoke the <hi>Truth</hi> unto the people, and proved this <hi>Ray</hi> openly to be a Deceiver among them, and judged him out of his own <hi>mouth,</hi> and ſo cleared my conſcience to the <hi>people,</hi> and ſo I came away with my <hi>friends</hi> in Peace, having cleared and <hi>diſcharged</hi> my conſcience unto them, by which they are eternally left without excuſe, whether they would <hi>hear</hi> or forbear, their <hi>blood</hi> will be upon their own <hi>heads,</hi> and ſo I leave them.</p>
               <p>Now upon the Day following it <hi>happened</hi> that a <hi>friend</hi> of mine did ſpeak with this <hi>Ray,</hi> who unto him did falſely affirm, that I ſaid I was the head
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:168214:27"/>
of the true Church, when as I never ſpoke any ſuch a thing, therefore I hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a meeting of the Baptiſts that day, and that this <hi>Ray</hi> was there, I &amp; ſeveral of my friends went unto this meeting, &amp; when I came at the houſe the dore was open, and I went in amongſt them, and this <hi>Ray</hi> was ſpeaking unto the people, and when he ſaw me he ſtopped his ſpeaking, and ſhut his book before I opened my mouth to ſpeak, and bid me be gone out of the houſe, and I ſaid, is thy ſpirit limited? is thy ſpirit bound? and he bid me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, and ſaid why did I diſturb them? and asked him, how did I diſturb you was not I ſilent until thou ſpoke to me? but guilt tormenting him within he could not forbear me, but called for the man of the houſe to command me out ſeveral times, but he was not amongſt them as they ſaid, ſo this <hi>Ray</hi> was much vexed and in much wrath, and one of their Elders, named <hi>Iohn Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi> of <hi>VVickin,</hi> ſtood up and puſhed me with his hand upon my breaſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times in much wrath, to have me out of the houſe, and I did not reſiſt him, &amp; he ſaid if I would not go out they would ſend for the officers; now let all people ſee what weapons they make uſe of, when one comes ſoberly and civilly without any violence amongſt them, and preſently to be in ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and confuſion, and rage, as they was, and threatning to ſend for the officers, whenas there was no violence offered by us, but here you might ſee what theſe people would do if they had a law to guard them as the Prieſts hath: then there was one man that had been hearing of them, and he ſpoke and ſaid to this <hi>Ray,</hi> you ſay they are deceivers, and they ſay you are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, now I would have you diſpute it, that thoſe that are ignorant might know which are the deceivers; but <hi>Ray</hi> ſlighted him, and ſaid, who are you? I know you not, &amp; would by no means have his deeds brought to the light to be tryed, but gets amongſt the blind where he cannot be ſeen, ſo then they brought the woman of the houſe to me, and ſhe bid me go out of her houſe, which I did not reſiſt, and ſo I called to <hi>Ray</hi> and told him he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of his doctrine, &amp; ſo I ſhoke off the duſt of my feet for a witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and ſo left them, and then they ſhut their dore, but poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple I do pitty you, to ſee how ignorantly and blindly you are led by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of Satan, to think that you are the Church of Chriſt, and none elſe, whenas your teachers dare not ſtand to maintain their doctrine, but flies away when they ſhould come to the proof, and calls for Officers when one comes in amongſt you without any carnal weapon; is this the doctrine of Chriſt which you talk ſo much of, or of Antichriſt? ſurely if I had been a deceiver and he a miniſter of Chriſt, then I could not have ſtopped his mouth, but he would have ſtopped mine, for the miniſters of Chriſt are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtop the mouths of gainſayers, but his mouth was ſtopped, yea, when he was buſie at that he calls preaching too, but my mouth he could not ſtop, and he was found the deceiver, whom truth put to ſilence, who was aſhamed of his doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:168214:27"/>
                  <hi>Oh people take heed how you reject ſo great Salvation, for this is the day of your viſitation, now you are warned by one, who amongſt you is counted a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, yet true, witneſſed in all your conſciences, by that which will either accuſe you, or excuſe you before the the throne of God, who am known to all the children of Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="document">
                           <head>The Excommunicaiion of <hi>Ezekiel Cater,</hi> &amp; <hi>Samuel Cater</hi> out of the Bapiſts ſociety, by <hi>Iohn Ray,</hi> with their Anſwer thereunto.</head>
                           <p>VVe two, namely, <hi>Ezekiel Cater,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Cater,</hi> being met together amongſt our friends, upon the <hi>4</hi> day of <hi>3</hi> month, waiting upon the Lord, there came three of the teachers of the baptiſed people, amongſt whom was one <hi>John Ray</hi> a chiefe Teacher, who came and ſaid he had a meſſage to deliver, but his meſſage was denyed, but he ſaid he would ſpeak, and ſo diſorderly ran into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words to this effect,</p>
                           <p>There being a generall meeting at Cambridge this week,<note place="margin">Excom John Ray.</note> where the Church of Chriſt was met together, and there it was agreed upon by the Elders, that <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Cater,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel Cater,</hi> who were formerly Elders of the church of Chriſt in this town, namely, Littleport, and being they have departed from the ſweet fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Church of Chriſt, &amp;c. and after ſo many admonitions, would not be reconciled, ſhould be delivered unto Satan, I was there appointed to be the meſſenger, and ſo he run on with his excommunication, according to their form, with their ſtoln words.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Reply.</hi> Now for the truths ſake, for which thou <hi>John Ray</hi> haſt caſt us out of your ſociety, we ſhall hereby cleare our ſelves from what is or may be caſt upon us in this matter, by thee <hi>John Ray,</hi> and the reſt of thy ſociety, whom we know to be moſt bitter ſlanderers of the truth.</p>
                           <p>This we deny that ever we was Elders in the church of Chriſt, you made us Elders in your church, who call your ſelves jews, and are not, but the Synagogue of Satan, out of which you have caſt us, but not before we forſaked you, we by the light of Ieſus Chriſt, through the love of God, ſeeing both you and we, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelves of acting and imitating the Apoſtles in our wils, with a blind zeal for life, but ſtrangers to the life and power; neither could witneſs the ſame infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible spirit as they had, as you know we all confeſſed, and therefore we had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what we got into our brains of their words, and ſo got a notion, with adding to our own imaginations of them, and wreſting the ſame with our fallible ſpirits, for we durſt not ſay it was infallible, as you alſo confeſſed your ſelves, then it muſt needs be fallible, for there are but two kindes of SPIRITS, and if not the <hi>INFALLIBLE,</hi> then the fallible; and though we did the very ſame things and ſpoke the ſame words and not from the ſame Spirit, it was all falſe and as nothing, as they that ſwore God lived ſwore falſely, for they that have not the Spirit of Chriſt are none of his, and his ſpirit is infallible in the leaſt meaſure, and thus you are ſhut out in all that you can do of your ſelves, with your formed Ordinances, and this we know, we was alſo ſtrangers to the Croſs of Chriſt, and the Light and Life and Power of Chriſt, which the Apoſtles lived in, and alſo the one Baptiſme of Chriſt without which none can be his Diſciples, ſo we was only jews outwardly, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the outſide, but within as foul as ever, as you alſo are, yet we ſay not but we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168214:28"/>
had a zeale in the ſame, though not according to knowledge, but now the true Light is ſprung in, through the mighty love of God towards us, ſo that we ſee the weakneſs of our own actings and formings in our own wils for life, and now are made willing through the power of God, to lay down our crowns at the feet of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and to wait in what he hath given us of his Light, and we have taſted of his powerful VVord through his gracious love towards us, and now we have a witneſs vvithin our ſelves, whenas before we knew it not, but murdered it as you alſo do and for this you have caſt us out of your ſociety, but not for fornication, as he was in that place of Scripture which you imitate,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> nor for making ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience, for we witneſs an increaſe of both, but the diſcerning and power is wanting in you, and ſo you do you know not what, but know this, we are not fallen to a looſer life, but to a more ſtricter ſevere life, for to ſerve the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, but remember this, that if they that believed your form to be the truth could but patter over a few words of faith, and call it theirs, and then according to your form they was put into the VVater, and taken out again, and then recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into your Church and communion, though no change of life or nature, and this muſt needs be the Synagogue of Satan, and this <hi>I Samuel Cater</hi> can vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for ſo have I baptiſed, and at you I learned, and you allovved of it, but novv my eye is opened, I do ſee it and do teſtifie againſt it, that all I did ſo by <hi>I</hi> deceived them, though then <hi>I</hi> confeſs it vvas ignorance, and ſo vvas yours, but novv you might ſee if you vvould, therefore it ſhall no more be called ignorance, but vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful blindneſs, but <hi>I</hi> knovv you vvill alledge you teach Godlineſs and holyneſs; but <hi>I</hi> anſvver, you run and the Lord never ſent you, as vve alſo did, therefore you profit not the people at all, and if you had not the VVords of Godlineſs and the form,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14, 15</note> then the Miniſters of Antichriſt vvould not be like the Ministers of Christ but you are, but <hi>I</hi> ſay your lives comes ſhort of vvhat you profeſs, for in them there is no change, but they that are Earthly Minded, and <hi>Covetous,</hi> are ſo ſtil, and your lives are in pride, ambition, and arrogancy, puffed up vvith your vain knovvledg, and vvith reſpect of perſons, and ſo are out of the faith of Chriſt and in vvrath and anger, and envy, and bitterneſs, and in lying, and ſlandering, and backbiting, and luſt, &amp; fleſhlineſs, we formerly being in the ſame Society do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it now our eys are open, out of which ſociety you have caſt us, and praiſed be the Lord that vve have eſcaped the ſnares of darkneſs, by the bright ſhining of his light into our dark hearts, to the vvhich light do vve ſpeak in you all, by it to read your ſelves, and judge your ſelves, for by it are you ſeen and judged to be in <hi>darkneſs</hi> and in confuſion, out of the faith and ſociety of the Saints, but theſe things do vve not ſpeak out of envy or Revenge, but for the clearing of the <hi>Truth</hi> and our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences from <hi>your ſlanderous tongues,</hi> and to lay oped your deceit and vvay of deluſion to the ſimple, that they may eſcape the deluſion vvhich vve vvas enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in, and that ſo you may proceed no further vvith it, that your folly might be manifeſted to all men, as theirs vvas vvho vvithſtood Moſes.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>E.C. S.C.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>A Copy of the moſt of the Queries aforeſaid was given to this <hi>Ray,</hi> but no Anſwer did he return.</p>
               <p>NOw a word to all you who are ſtil in your own formings, ſelfe-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctings,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> and imitatings, you are acting in that nature which is at en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with God, which is not ſubject to the Law of God, neither can; ſo all your formings and actings is in vain, for it is not from life, but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168214:28"/>
from death, for life; but life comes from death, for in the deſtruction of death is life obtained, therefore to the light of the Lord Jeſus in all your conſciences take heed, which is the witneſs for God, to which I ſpeak in you all, which witneſſeth for God againſt the ſecrets of your hearts, which reproves you in ſecret for your ſecret actions, and deeds of darkneſs, and it will ſearch you through, and let you ſee what you can witneſs of the work of God in you hearts, for all this your long and great profeſſion, and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming your ſelves of the Church and faith of Chriſt, and Saints in Chriſt, ſo if you can witneſs yet the earth quakes, and that the earth is yet remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of its place, and mountains removed by the eye of faith, and if the vail of darkneſs be yet rent. Is not the firſt man yet ſtanding, and the firſt Image, and the Serpent head? for while you are ſtrangers to the light, and your minds are from the light, you are wandred and ſtrayed in the pathes of darknes, and ſo are the children of darkneſs, in whom the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs rules, even the Serpent who is head in man, but the promiſe is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> the ſeed of the woman ſhal bruiſe the Serpents head; but you are acting in your own wills and wiſdome, the Serpent is your head, and you are not yet come to witneſs the firſt promiſe fulfilled, but are ſtill in the fall, under the power of Darkneſs, in the diſobedience, and ſtrangers unto the Croſs, and ſo have no part in Chriſt in that nature, for none comes to have a right in Chriſt but through the Croſs, for as many as are baptiſed into Chriſt, are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into his death, and they that are dead with him do live with him, and they that are dead are freed from ſin, and they that are in Chriſt are new creatures; old things are paſſed away, and all things become new, but they that are not in Chriſt are ſtill in old Adam, and ſo in the fall under the curſe, and under deaths dominion, drove out from the preſence of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the earth, and death reigns over all, from <hi>Adam</hi> until <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14.</note> of what profeſſion ſoever; therefore now read your ſelves by the light which comes from Ieſus Chriſt, and ſhines into your dark hearts, and ſearcheth the heart and tryeth the reins, and maketh manifeſt the ſecrets, to which light I am made manifeſt, and by it witneſſed in you all, and unto it I do direct your mindes, for the turning of your mindes from the darkneſs to the light; all you that have a deſire to find the way of truth, in what form ſoever that thereby you may come to ſee how you have been wandered and ſcattered in the many wayes of darkneſs, in the land of darkneſs, in this cloudy &amp; dark day, as ſheep without a ſhepheard, being carryed about after the voyce of ſtrangers, from the ſhepheard of your ſouls, therefore hearken no more without to thoſe that cry, lo here, or lo there is Chriſt, and ſo draws your minds without to ſeek for a Chriſt without, and a redemption, and a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication without, and a righteouſneſs without, and a God withou; but turn your minds within, for it is to be found within if ever you find; for there is no way to come unto the true knowledg of the truth, or of God, or of Chriſt but by that of God within, for what is to be known of God is manifeſt within, and the ſame which deſcended, the ſame doth aſcend, and ſo the way to God is to be found within, by the light which manifeſts death and ſlayes death, do not you read the parable of the woman that had loſt the piece of ſilver, and could not find it until ſhe had turned into the houſe and light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the candle &amp; ſwept the houſe, &amp; then ſhe found that which ſhe had loſt,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:168214:29"/>
and rejoyced with her neighbors;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 15.8.9. <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.27. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.4.</note> now the Spirit of man is the candle of the Lord, and his life was the light of men, ſo turn in your minds to the light of the Lord Jeſus, which if you love it to bring your deeds to it, wil let you ſee the deeds of darkneſs, and the pathes of death, and it wil alſo ſearch your hearts, and make manifeſt your inward parts, and let you ſee what you have loſt, and as you love this light, and likes to retain it in your minds, and by it to be guided, it wil lead you out of all the crooked &amp; frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard waies of darkneſs into the light of life, and ſo to come to find and know the voice of the true ſhepheard, who is come to ſeek out and gather all his ſcattered ſheep out from amongſt the mountains and valleys, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes and crooked pathes wherein they have been ſcattered and ſtrayed in the land of Darkneſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.3.</note> and to gather them together into one flock, into one way, into one ſheepfold, &amp; he alone wil be their ſhepheard, and this you ſhall come to witneſs; as you love this light and follow it, it wil lead you out of your many Forms, and many wayes, into one way, out of your own wiſdome and imaginations wherein you have been building Babel, and this wil ſtrip you of all your own righteouſneſs wherewith you have cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red over your deceitful hearts, and it wil lay your deceits before you, and bring you to judgement, and if you love this light and follow it, and be willing to wait upon it, out of your own wills, and wiſdome, and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and carnall thoughts, reaſonings, and conſultations, and ſelfe-ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and imatating it wil lead you to know the voice of the true ſhepheard within you from the voice of the ſtranger, and ſo to know the precious from the precious from the vile, he who ſaith, I am the light, he ſaith, I am the good ſhepheard who wil bring you to know the way and the dore into the ſheepfold, if you do not run out in your own wills, and ſeek to climb up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, for the way is but one, and he that ſaith I am the light, ſaith I am the way, and I am the dore into the ſheepfold: ſo if you turn from the Light and ſtumble at the light, you ſtumble at all and ſo fall, but if you love the light, and be willing to follow the light, it will lead you through all, and to deny your ſelves and to take up his Croſs unto thy ſelf, and to paſs through good report, and evil report, through perſecution &amp; through death,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.8.</note> and the way wil not be grievous but joyous, and ſo you wil come into the way, and in at the dore unto the ſheepfold, and ſo into the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and into the life, and into the power, and into the faith of the Saints, where all live in union in one, united by one into one body, the end of all jarring and jangling diviſions and diſputes, therefore ſaid the Apoſtle, where is the wiſe, where is the diſputer of this world? hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdome of this world,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> therefore I do you call to come out from amongſt them, and be ye ſeperate, and touch no unclean thing, and I will receive you ſaith the Lord, and I wil be unto you a father, and ye ſhal be my Sons &amp; Daughters; now you are called, and this is the day of your viſitation for now light is come into the world, and if you like to retain it in your minds happy are you,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17 18.</note> but if not, by it you are left without excuſe, and it wil judge you at the laſt day, for he that loves the light ſhal not walk in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but ſhal have the light of life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but he that doth evil hates the light which is his condemnation;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.12.</note> now the way is plain to all ſimple ones, who have a deſire to find it declared by a friend and witneſs to the eternall Truth: who am called,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I. P.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
